<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A figure of the true &amp; spiritual tabernacle, according to the inward temple or house of God in the spirit. : Whereunto is added the eight vertues or godlynesses. / Set forth by H.N. and by him perused, and more evidently declared.</title>
            <title>Figuer des warachitigen unde geistelicke tabeinakels. English</title>
            <author>Niclaes, Hendrik, 1502?-1580?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 117 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097873</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171452</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2574:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A figure of the true &amp; spiritual tabernacle, according to the inward temple or house of God in the spirit. : Whereunto is added the eight vertues or godlynesses. / Set forth by H.N. and by him perused, and more evidently declared.</title>
                  <title>Figuer des warachitigen unde geistelicke tabeinakels. English</title>
                  <author>Niclaes, Hendrik, 1502?-1580?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 195, [15] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: En figuer des warachitigen unde geistelicke tabeinakels.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Familists.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Virtues.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FIGURE of the True &amp; Spiritual TABERNACLE, According to the inward Temple or Houſe of God in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added the Eight Vertues or Godlyneſſes.</p>
            <p>Set forth by <hi>H. N.</hi> and by him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and more evidently declared.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Temple of God was opened in heaven, and the Ark of his Teſtament was ſeen in his Temple, <bibl>Apoca. 12.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, and he ſhall dwell with them: and they ſhall be his people: And he God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with them, ſhall be their God, <bibl>Apo. 21. 1 Cor. 3. 2 Cor. 6.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-ſpread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing now that God hath exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his mercy on us, and through his grace<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod 25. Eze. 40.41, 42.43, 44. Apoc 21.22.</note> reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made known unto us in our Spirit, his true Tabernacle or Temple (wherein his Holy God-ſervice is uprightly miniſtred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth.)</p>
            <p>Therefore are we become occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned or moved, even out of Love, to witneſs our Figure forth writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb facs="tcp:171452:4"/>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ex. 25.31. Eze. 43. Act. 7. c. Heb. 8. a.</note> in Letters, this preſent Figure, or Pre-figuration of the ſame Tabernacle or Temple of God, together with his true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices in the Spirit (namely in the fore-front, in the holy, and in the moſt holy) before all lovers of the truth, and of the true God-ſervice, and to ſet it forth under the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The bearing of which true being or form in the Spirit; is<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ex. 29. c. Jer. 23. a. 30. b. 31. d. Eze. 36.37.</note> that which God regardeth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of the man. For even therefore (namely) to the ſetting up of this ſame true God-ſervice in the Spirit, under the obedience of the Love, hath God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through his benign or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Love, revealed or declared in<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 13. b Epheſ. 3. a. Col 1. c.</note> heaven, his true Sanctuarie or Tabernacle unto us, as alſo the fore-front, the holy and the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:171452:4"/>
holy of the ſame: And granted to diſcern and underſtand the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie or ſecretneſs thereof, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo choſen us to the miniſtration of the ſame; under the obedience of the Love; to the end that now in this laſt time<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa 2. a. 60, 61, 62. Jer. 31 33. Eze. 36 37. Ioel 2.3. b. Mich 4. a. Zach. 8 a. Act. 2.</note> the truth or veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame Tabernacle of God ſhould alwayes and for evermore be miniſtred among the children of men, under the obedience of the Love, to a conſecrating or ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the fore-front, and of the holy, and to the ſetting up again, or reſtoring of the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Dan 9.</note> daily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering which hath ceaſed for a long time, for which cauſe likewiſe, the fore-front and the holy, hath been ſo utterly ruined, or laid waſt with abominations among the children of men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which conſecrating or ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of the fore-front, and of
<pb facs="tcp:171452:5"/>
the holy; as alſo the ſetting up of the daily offering, and of the true God-ſervice among the children of men, cometh to paſs altogether to<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eph 1 a.</note> the laud &amp; praiſe of the glory of God, and to the ſalvation or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the children of men, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe men which are good of will, alſo believe on the Love, ſubmit them humbly to the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſervice of Love, and ſo have a luſt to the eſtabliſhing the Promiſes of God the Father.</p>
            <closer>Take it to heart.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Reader.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the ſingle-minded ones, whoſe love is agreeable with us, in one ſpirit of the Love, be health and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough, yee dearly beloved, that our intent and purpoſe was to make but a ſmall preamble or prologue before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Glaſs of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:171452:6"/>
yet is it now notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fallen out otherwiſe. For the Prologue is grown to be more then we our ſelves meant it ſhould. But yet the labour beſtowed therein, hath not been tedious unto us.<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Cor. 13. a.</note> For the Love maketh all painful travel and labour eaſie, and her ſervice is not tedious, neither doth ſhe think any time too long, wherein ſhe may further the good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore is our hope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that it is all come to paſs for the beſt, and ſhall likewiſe be looked into by every one for a very profitable labour unto edification: in aſmuch doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as it is all ſerviceable to the inducing or guiding in of men to the holy underſtanding of the Glaſs of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:171452:6"/>
and to the Love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Alſo I did not purpoſe to let this Figure of the true and ſpiritual Tabernacle, go forth with the Glaſs of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to ſet it forth with other writings after the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or going forth of the ſame ſaid Glaſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But for as much as we have ſeen into or perceived, that it was very needful, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and ſerviceable to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh or ſet forth the ſame Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, to give thereby an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence or underſtanding of the inward ſpiritual Tabernacle, and to be a furtherance of the mans ſalvation; Therefore could we not through the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Love, conceal or keep back the ſame any longer; But have for the Loves ſake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:171452:7"/>
the Righteouſneſs, placed the ſame to ſtand next after the introduction, to the holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Glaſs of Righteouſneſs: And next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of the book of the ſaid Glaſs, by which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the Prologue is become ſo much the larger.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Yet is our hope notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that neither the good willing Reader, nor any one elſe, will ſtumble or take of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at the muchneſs or plenty of writing that is uſed before the beginning of the Book; but rejoyce them ſo much the more therein, and take a greater pleaſure and liking therein, then if we had left out the ſame. For it is doubtleſs a more plain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring or opening of that forenamed Book, intituled
<pb facs="tcp:171452:7"/>
the Glaſs of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is true, that it doth not accord or ſute very well to make large Preambles, or large Prologues. Howbeit we have leaſt eſteemed of the Clarkly form of congruity or artificial ſutableneſs: But have much rather had our reſpect bent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which is ſerviceable unto the good, and to the holy underſtanding, whereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 1. b. 1 a. 3. a. Col. 1. c.</note> riches of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God the Father, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſalvation, and to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1. b. 1 Ioh. 1 a.</note> that which we have ſeen with our eyes, and heard with our ears.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But although now that we do not utter forth or write the ſame, according to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial skill, or Clarkly cunning of manly wit; Nor yet with
<pb facs="tcp:171452:8"/>
painted or flowred words, or garniſhed ſpeech of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, wiſe, or famous Clarks: But even with a plain and mother or common ſtyle or form: Yet is notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our requeſt, that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Hearers of the ſame our writing, would not take offence thereat: and ſo in any ſuch reſpect, deſpiſe or make leſs account of our labour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is plain, and not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed or ſet forth according to the skill of Art; But that they would become all of one minde with us in the Love, to the end that every one might likewiſe through the Love, be partaker with us of the Grace and mercy, which God is now extending on us little and poor ones, through his Love.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb facs="tcp:171452:8"/>8. For unto us doth God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the health and life of our ſalvation out of his heavenly being, and hath called and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen us thereunto, becauſe that we ſhould be his miniſters in his Love, to the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to reveal even ſo through us under the ſervice of obedience in the Love, his ſecret myſteries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law, according to the Propheſying of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and according to the Godly Word of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="9">9.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Act. 2. b.</note> All which former ſervices, have to a unity under the Love, Propheſied on this time and ſervice of Love, for that the glory of God might be great in the laſt time through the Love: And ſo the Peace become prepared on
<pb facs="tcp:171452:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171452:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171452:10"/>
earth according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Therefore let no man have his regard bent either to the method, or artificial skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, or yet to the unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Art; But unto that whereunto our ſervice of the gratious Word extendeth, (namely to the Love) and to let every one become aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with us, into one Spirit of the lovely being, under the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Love, that the ſervice of Love may to an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of peace, be ſpread abroad over all the world.</p>
            <p n="11">11. For that cauſe, O yee ſingle-minded, good, willing ones, to the righteouſneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply you all, with a good will and an humble heart to the Love and her ſervice: And
<pb facs="tcp:171452:10"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Act. 2 d.</note> permit your ſelves to be baptized or waſhed in the name of the Love, to the forgiveneſs of your ſins, that ye may even ſo be renewed, refreſhed and reformed through the Love and her ſervice. Suffer not in any wiſe<note n="(g)" place="margin">Math. 18. a. Io. 3. a.</note> the deceitful ſlights, nor the wicked thoughts to have any dwelling place in you; But through the ſervice of Love, and of the gracious Word, become you turned about to the obedient and little children, that the Love may be planted in you with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Unto this ſame ſervice of Love, ſee that ye become all agreeably minded: For it ſhall all periſh and conſume away to nothing, namely all manner of knowledge and God-ſervices,
<pb facs="tcp:171452:11"/>
which are come or riſen up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day or light of the Love.<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Cor. 13 b.</note> But the Love ſhall not periſh, nor yet ceaſe, but their ſervice ſhall continue for ever.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whoſoever likewiſe do not aſſemble them under the love, they ſhall be ſcattered abroad. For the Love is the Light of the world:<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ioh. 8. b.</note> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo follows after her, walketh not in darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The Love is the gracious word of the Lord, or<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ioh. 6. f.</note> bread of Life, which is come unto us out of heaven. For the Love is eſſentially the very true good,<note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. a.</note> the head-ſum of the commandment,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Col. 3. b.</note> and the bond of perfection.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Through which Love, the ſecret Treaſures of God the Father,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Eph. 1. b. 2. a. b.</note> and the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb facs="tcp:171452:11"/>
Riches of his ſpiritual and heavenly goods be revealed.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Whoſoever then doth not apply himſelf to the Love: but refuſeth her, or deſpiſeth her ſervice, and is grown ſelf-wiſe or ſelf-minded againſt the ſame, by means of his aſpiring or loftie knowledge, ſuch a one remaineth a Baſtard, or a Stranger from the inheritance of God, and cannot alſo inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Riches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="17">17. But the children of Love, are the upright heirs of God. For they are of a good nature and diſpoſition, namely<note n="(p)" place="margin">Col. 3. a.</note> meek-minded, loving and peaceable.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Even ſuch be all thoſe likewiſe, which do with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearts ſubmit them under the Love, and are obedient
<pb facs="tcp:171452:12"/>
to the requiring of her ſervice.</p>
            <p n="19">19. And though they be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with many ſins,<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.</note> yet are their ſins forgiven them, and blotted out through the Love, and in their repentance for their ſins, they walk with a good conſcience, both before God and men.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Behold ſuch is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice or office of the Love. The Almighty God vouchſafe to enable and ſtrengthen us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto through his Love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171452:12"/>
            <head>THE FIGURE Of the true and Spiritual Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God: Witneſſed and Figured forth by <hi>H. N.</hi> according to the true being or form of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple or Houſe of God, and that in every reſpect according to thar form, even as the very eſſence or being thereof was by the holy Spirit of the Lord revealed and declared unto him out of the heavenly Truth.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination had a long time ſtood bent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſervice of Love: And that I had longed even with a fervent deſire, that the true God-ſervice might
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171452:13"/>
once flouriſh out of the Love (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the peace and ſalvation of all people, and to a true declaring of the ſpiritual Tabernacle of God, in the holy of his holy ones.) Therfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the true Tabernacle or<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lev. 26.26. b 2 Cor. 6 b. Apoc 21. a.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of God by grace out of the Love of God the Father, revealed unto me in the Spirit, through Gods heavenly revelation, to the end that I ſhould conſider of or note there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the true God-ſervice, which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to the bleſſing of the earth, and to the peace &amp; ſalvation of all people.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the which I at the firſt, thought not upon the noting or marking of any thing elſe, but only of the moſt holy and moſt pure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ex 26 d. 40. a b. c. Heb. 9. a</note> the mercy ſeat, and the Ark of the Covenant, together with the manifold glorious riches, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous garniſhing. All which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in their pure and perfect beauty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Through which Revelation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding out of the heavenly being, I rejoyced me far beyond meaſure: But there came not into my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171452:13"/>
ſo preſently at the firſt to conſider or note, the holy and his daily offering or God ſervice, and the fore front, nor yet the ſervice of the Levites and Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But when I once remembred the holy of the ſame Tabernacle, and his ſervice of the holy offering, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the forgiveneſs of ſins: then turned I my ſelf to the ſame, for to behold the daily offering for God-ſervice miniſtred therein, becauſe I might ſee, and alſo underſtand the daily offering in the holy, and the Altar, whereon the debt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, ſin-offering, &amp; death-offering is offered &amp; burnt to a forgivneſs of ſins.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I alſo noted the fore-front: the which is a difference<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eze. 44. a. b.</note> betwixt the holy of the Tabernacle of God, and the unholy of the uncircumciſed hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-ſhip.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In which forefront, the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites and Prieſts in their ſervice, and in their requiring of the righteouſneſs, are to<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ex. 27 c Lev. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b Num. 16. b Eze. 43, 44,</note> prepare the daily offering, betwixt the holy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171452:14"/>
and the unholy, betwixt the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed and the uncircumciſed, whereby the Believers might have a free en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the God-ſervice uſed in the holy, for to offer up holy offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſuch as are delightful unto God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Now then did I alſo call to mind, the Levites and the Prieſts,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ioel 1. b: 2. b.</note> which ought to have their daily God-ſervice, for the aſſiſting of the little and weak ones, betwixt the fore-front and the Altar of the ſelf-making of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in the holy, for to reveal and make known unto the Believers, the free entrance into the holy, and in the ſame ſervice, daily to inform or train up the people which give over them ſelves thereunto, with the word of the holy underſtanding, till that the ſervice of God in the holy, be in that ſort in full and due manner executed or performed, namely that the death-offering, as well as the ſin offering, be quite and clean burnt or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, upon the Altar, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171452:14"/>8. Through which ſervice and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the death offering in the holy,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Matth 27 Mark 15.</note> the vail that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt holy departeth away, or is put off. Into which moſt holy, only the High Prieſt doth<note n="(g)" place="margin">Exo 30. Lev. 16. Heb 9 10. b.</note> enter, and revealeth the mercy Seat, the everlaſting forgiveneſs of ſins, and doth cleanſe it all in the holy, through his blood of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. The which is the Love, the flood of the everlaſting life, and the eternal day-light of the cleerneſs of God, and alſo the uncovering of the face of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Behold when as I now bent my ſelf to conſider hereon, and began adviſedly to look into the ſame, then found I, that both the holy and the fore-front, were utterly laid<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 74.79. a. Eze. 5.22, 23, 24.</note> waſt, and deſpiſed and trodden under foot, by the heathen or uncircumciſed ones, and the Altar appointed for the ſervice of a daily<note n="(i)" place="margin">Dan. 7, 8, 9.4. Eſd. 10. 1 Mac. 2, 3, 4. Rom. 11. a.</note> offering in the holy, was altogether defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <p n="10">10. I alſo beheld, that the holy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171452:15"/>
City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> lay<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 64 c. Lam 1.2 a.</note> broke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> down and deſtroyed, Sion as a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or like one forſaken, and Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſperſed and captivated among al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people, and that the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal 79. a. Lam. 5 a.</note> ſtrangers inhabited Iſraels inheritance, the lands lying about <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And in the holy place I ſaw nothing but<note n="(m)" place="margin">Dan. 9.11. c. Math. 24. b.</note> abomination of deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The<note n="(n)" place="margin">Dan. 11, 12. 4 Eſd. 10. c.</note> daily offering had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ceaſed a long time, for which cauſe likewiſe there was no daily God-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the holy.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Moreouer I ſaw not in the fore-front, nor yet in the holy, any<note n="(o)" place="margin">3. King. 19. b. Rom. 11. a.</note> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, or yet Prieſts, for to Miniſter the office, to the preparing of the offering, betwixt the fore-front and the Altar.</p>
               <p n="13">13. For which cauſe ſake of the abomination of deſolation, I ſaw no free entrance into the holy, for to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſin offering in the holy. And ſo by that occaſion there chanced likewiſe no forgiveneſs of ſins.</p>
               <p n="14">14. When I now beheld, that all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171452:15"/>
theſe holy things were thus grown to ruine, or laid waſt:<note n="(p)" place="margin">Lam. 1, 2, 3. Dan. 8. 4 Eſd. 10.</note> it grieved me ſore, and I lamented greatly for the Sanctuary of the holy offering, (namely, the holy with his holy and ſafe-making ſervice) the which the heathen or the uncircumciſed<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal. 79. a Lam. 5 a.</note> that were come into the Lands heritage, had utterly polluted and laid waſt.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Which heathen or uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed ones, have not alſo in any true manner underſtood the holy God-ſervice of Iſrael: Howbeit ſeeing they have preſumed to buſie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about the ſame, alſo enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and taken it upon them, ſo have they even everywhere polluted and made it deſolate with<note n="(r)" place="margin">Eze. 28. Dan. 9.</note> abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And for that cauſe did I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment moſt chiefly, the holy and his daily offering.</p>
               <p n="16">16. In that now I did moſt of all lament the holy of the Tabernacle of God, and his holy and ſafe-making ſervice, it was doubtleſs therefore, namely, becauſe I perceived that the ſame holy was ſo utterly laid waſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171452:16"/>
that there was no true offering or ſervice of the holy, or ſafe-making offering uſed therein, and for that the arrogancie<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ezek 44. a</note> of the heathen or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed ones, had with their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and abominations gotten the upper hand in the ſame, and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it all, laid it deſolate or waſte, which deſolation and abominations of the uncircumciſed did ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly trouble and grieve me, that I could not pacifie my ſelf in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing and lamenting that came over me touching this abomination of deſolation. For I ſaw that there could no reconciliation nor forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſins come to paſs, but through the daily offering or God-ſervice in the holy; and the ſin did ſtill daily augment or grow to a great increaſe or multiplying.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Becauſe of this abomination of deſolation, and for that the daily offering was ceaſed by reaſon of the ſins<note n="(t)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 14, 15 Math. 4. b.</note> which had ſo abundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: And alſo for that I ſaw no end or going under of the ſin, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171452:16"/>
became I, even through great grief of heart, crying out unto God and ſaid,</p>
               <p n="18">18. O Lord, Lord, when wilt thou according to thy promiſes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together again, and be gracious unto thy people Iſrael, and bring them unto their Reſt? And when ſhall I beſeech thee, thy holy<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mat. 2. b</note> Tabernacle be conſecrated and cleanſed from the abomination of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation?</p>
               <p n="19">19. For ſeeing now that the holy and the fore-front of thy Tabernacle is thus utterly laid waſte: Alſo that thy daily offering hath ceaſed for a time, and that into thoſe places the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Dan. 9. b</note> abominations of deſolation are come or entred (where through likewiſe, the iniquity is grown excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great and abundant) ſo goeth it therefore doubtleſs very evil and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable with thy people.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Foraſmuch as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth waſte, or overthrown, Sion ſitteth as a widdow, or as one forſaken. And that thy holy Temple hath not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171452:17"/>
his declaring or clearneſs upon the Mount Sion within <hi>Jeraſalem,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth not thy ſalvation O God, appear or ſhine thereout. The ſin alſo is not put off or done away,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 19. c. Rom. 11. c.</note> nor the ungodlyneſs debarr'd or put away from Jews.</p>
               <p n="21">21. For that cauſe likewiſe, there cometh to paſs no<note n="(z)" place="margin">Heb. 9 b</note> forgiveneſs of ſins there, nor yet any cleanſing of the ſpotted conſcience; for the belief or faith<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act 15 b Rom. 8. a.</note> whereby one is juſtified from the ſin, is<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 7 c.</note> taken away from the earth: And the iniquity encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more and more, even unto the very worſt,<note n="(c)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 14. b. 15. a. Math. 24. b</note> for it hath gotten the upper hand: And we find no refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſhaking in our ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171452:17"/>
               <head>The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <p>THe whileſt I thus beheld this ſtate of deſolation, and pittied the ſame ſo exceedingly, and lamented there over before the moſt high, ſo heard I a mighty<note n="(a)" place="margin">3 King 19. Act. 1. a.</note> ſound or noiſe proceeding out of heaven, and it ruſhed like a tempeſtuous wind, with great force over the earth, in ſuch wiſe that the earth was afraid, and quaked by reaſon thereof. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which lay and ſlept under the earth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ez. 37. Dan. 12. b. 4 Eſd. 3. d. Ioh. 5. c. 1 Cor. 15. <hi>f.</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. l.</note> awaked, ſome to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, ſome to perpetual contempt and reproach.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now I marvelled greatly at this viſion and ſaid, O God, how<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 17. a Rom. 11.</note> wonderful and incomprehenſible are thy works before all underſtanding of the fleſh!</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171452:18"/>3. Behold this miraculous work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come to paſs among us upon earth; becauſe that the Prophecie ſhould be fulfilled<note n="(d)" place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> that was ſaid unto <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet in times paſt, come to paſs in theſe laſt times.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And I looked and behold <hi>Daniel</hi> who (according to the word of the Lord) had reſted a long time, even until this ſame laſt time,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> ſtood up and appeared and came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, in his part and office, for to keep and execute the judgement againſt the abominations of deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which were grown up on the earth. And the Propheſies which (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of the Lord) had remained<note n="(f)" place="margin">Da. 12. b.</note> ſealed to all unto this laſt time, were opened, and their myſteries revealed in clearneſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And through this Revelation and opening or declaring of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, I was greatly afraid. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as I ſaw no righteouſneſs of God to have the upper hand upon the earth. But that the iniquity, did<note n="(g)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 14, 15. a. Math. 24.</note> lord or bear rule generally, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171452:18"/>
Reigned on the earth, therefore was greatly perplexed, and altogether feeble and comfortleſs in my ſelf, fearing leaſt that I ſhould periſh with all the ungodly of the wicked world, for the manifold iniquities cauſe, which I beheld ſo to abound over the whole earth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For through the opening of the Propheſies that were ſealed too, there was revealed unto me, that all thoſe that dwelt upon earth, were departed away or eſtranged<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſa. 14. a Rom. 3. b.</note> from the living God and his truth. And moreover before the<note n="(i)" place="margin">Iſa. 29. b.</note> opening of the Propheſies that were ſealed up, no man upon earth, how prudent or wiſe ſoever he was, had any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in God, nor yet had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or underſtood any of Gods holy knowledge.</p>
               <p n="7">7. This ſame ſeemed before me very terrible, yea even to be a very hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing to look into, becauſe that the miſunderſtanding, or the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance touching the Being of God, and the ungodlyneſs had ſo multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171452:19"/>
it ſelf upon earth; therefore was I very exceedingly afraid, and became marvellous faint-hearted and ſtrengthleſs; And I continued la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting greatly over the ſame, and grew likewiſe altogether comfortleſs in my ſelf.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now in the time while I was grown thus utterly void of comfort in my lamentation that I made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great wrong that I ſaw upon the earth, ſo did there appear in my ſight<note n="(k)" place="margin">Dan. 8, 9, 10.</note> the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> and he came unto me, but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not with me ſtill in my ſight.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But ſo long as he was with me, and that I beheld him, I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by him; but when he departed from me, and that I ſaw him not, then had I no reſt, peace, or comfort in my ſoul: Alſo no people on earth could comfort me, ſaving only <hi>Gabriel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. For when he came unto me and talked with me, I was of good chear. And if <hi>Gabriel</hi> had not ſtrengthened or comforted me, then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171452:19"/>
could I not have remained alive. For there was ſhewed unto me, both fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and wonderful things: the like whereof I had never ſeen or heard before.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For the dead aroſe out of<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eze. 37. Math. 27.</note> the grave, and lived. And the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made manifeſt their own condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation through their unrighteouſneſs wherein they had lived unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they deſcended into the<note n="(m)" place="margin">Apo. 9. a 20. b.</note> bottomleſs pit to their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on for evermore.</p>
               <p n="12">12. I beheld the miſery of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, but I could have no compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the extending of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe or pitty towards them,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Apo. 18. c</note> but rather rejoyced me for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicity and condemnations cauſe. For they were well worthy<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ap 16 a</note> of the ſame, becauſe of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="13">13. I alſo rejoyced me greatly<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. c. Apo. 20. a.</note> in the Reſurrection of the righteous, becauſe I ſaw they roſe up ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly from death, and went into the everlaſting life: And for that their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171452:20"/>
domination was with God and the Lamb; for I ſaw that they were both worthy of that, and likewiſe to Reign upon the earth.</p>
               <p n="14">14. With theſe Righteous ones, after that they were riſen, have I ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and eaten and drunk with them;<note n="(r)" place="margin">Dan. 12. b Sapl. 3. a. Math. 13. c.</note> their bodies gliſtred like the clearneſs of the Sun: And they have ſpoken ſecret things with me, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the myſticalneſs of God, of the Kingdom of heaven, of the true reſurrection of the Godly men, of their joy in the everlaſting life: And of the purging of the earth in the judgement of the dreadful Almighty God which cometh over all ungodly<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jude 1.</note> Being or nature.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The which Almighty God hath more made up him ſelf, and coming over the earth, he cometh<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mal 3. a.</note> with righteouſneſs (like as the ſame God hath ſpoken thereof by his ſervants the Prophets in times paſt) for to ſave his people, to the end that thoſe which are worthy of the Life, might live for evermore, and ſo may reign
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171452:20"/>
everlaſtingly upon<note n="(u)" place="margin">Apoc. 5.16, 18, 19, 20.</note> the earth in all love: Alſo for to damn thoſe in the everlaſting death which are not his people: who for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cauſe are worthy of damnation and of death; To the end they may no longer reign upon the earth, with their unrighteouſneſs: But that they might be baniſhed or put away from the earth, and damned and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the hell, and that the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit may even ſo with them be ſhut up, and their condemnation to endure for ever and ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:171452:21"/>
               <head>The third Chapter.</head>
               <p>WHen as I now beheld, ſuch a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity of the deadly or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eſtate, hanging over the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men for their ſins cauſe: and that ſuch a dreadful judgement<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10. c</note> of the Fires vehement cruelty, was coming unto them, to a ſuppreſſion of the enemies of God: And that ſuch an unfortunate ſtate of miſery (the which the Lord hath alſo let me ſee, taſte and feel) hung over their heads; Then was I ſore grieved and afflicted in my heart, in ſuch ſort that I became exceedingly diſmayed or uncaſed, and could well have vouchſafed, that there had been no man upon the earth, becauſe of the wo and grief which I ſaw coming over them for their ſins cauſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But that which did moſt of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171452:21"/>
grieve my heart, was this, that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that all thoſe that were born upon earth out of blood, are out of their earthly birth, inclined to<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 6.8. d. Pſal. 51 a.</note> nothing elſe but iniquity: and with their unrighteouſneſs are minded to deſtruction. That their laſt is bent to nothing elſe but unto error; that they alſo are utterly ignorant in all Godly things: and that they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (if they become not in their underſtanding recovered, through the Love and her ſervice, or renewed<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. a Rom. 12. c Eph. 4. c.</note> or born again in their Spirit) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape the ſevere Judgement of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When I thus beheld the ſame according to the truth, that it was ſo utterly unknown unto all people of the earth, and that they did every one follow after the ſelf wiſdom of the fleſh to their condemnation, then was I much more grieved in my mind, and I bowed down my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Majeſtie of God who is in heaven and ſaid;</p>
               <p n="4">4. O Lord God of heaven, Thou
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171452:22"/>
that art a God of the living, full of Grace and all goodneſs, and haſt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Sapi. 1. b.</note> created all, whatſoever is any thing, becauſe it ſhould be, and that it might go well with the ſame: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now thou haſt made up thy ſelf for to judge the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Act. 17 d</note> circuit of the earth with righteouſneſs; ſo be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gracious I beſeech thee, to<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iob 14. b. Pſal. 138. a.</note> the work of thine own hands, to the end there may now in the laſt time, ſome ſouls remain over upon the earth, and that<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 10. c. Rom 9. c.</note> the remnant O God might be ſaved</p>
               <p n="5">5. Shew O God, thy mercie upon us, through thy bountiful Love Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo that we all of us, out of our earthly births are<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſa. 14. a. Rom. 3. b.</note> an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people, void of underſtanding, and by nature are clean contrary-minded unto thy wiſdom, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining therefrom: And have no luſt or affection towards thy infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, nor any pleaſure in the word of thy ſervants, which preſent or hold forth thy ſalvation unto us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obedience of thy Love, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171452:22"/>
we do all out of our earthly birth ſtand affected towards our ſelves, and do moſt gladly give ear to our ſelves and our own wiſdom of the fleſh, which floweth of our ſelf min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and fleſhly heart.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That is verily the ſin and the rebelliouſneſs or reſiſtance commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt thee O God, by all ſpirits of unregenerated men, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traryneſs againſt thee of all ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and good-thinking Scripture-learned ones.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Therefore O God rebuke and nurture us with thy Law or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and with the Doctrine of thy Commandments, and humble our hearts to the obeying of thy holy gracious Word and ſervice of Love, that we may be reformed of our wicked or contrary nature, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come underſtanding acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding to the Law or Doctrine of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments whereby we may O God accompliſh thy will.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Rebuke<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal 6.38. a. Ier. 10. c.</note> us not in thy wrath, and chaſten us not in thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171452:23"/>
but ſhake out the ſame over the ungodly, which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes O God againſt thee, and like or allow not of thee.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Deſtroy us not ſo utterly all alike, that the the great horror of deſolation come not over us all to our deſtruction, but that there may yet a remnant find Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; And that they (even like as in the former time<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen. 6, 7, 8.</note> of <hi>Noah</hi>) may now alſo in theſe laſt perilous times, remain preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171452:23"/>
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>BEhold the whileſt I ſtill lamented on this faſhion, the Angel <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi> appeared unto me again, whom I had in my ſight before, and he ſtrengthened my mind: For I was grown almoſt paſt recoverie, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my feebleneſs and faintheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then when my heart was a little refreſhed, then was it ſaid unto me: Ariſe, and be of good chear; for thou haſt found grace before God the moſt highſt, to declare his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the children of men, and alſo for to witneſs under the obedience of the Love,<note n="(a)" place="margin">4 Glaſ. 33.</note> unto the people upon the earth, the true God-ſervice which God regardeth, to the end that all thoſe which believe on the Love,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171452:24"/>
and ſubmit themſelves thereunder, may be ſaved, and that thoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe which refuſe the ſame, alſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Love, and allow not of her ſervice, may juſtly receive their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto condemnation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore turn now thy face again to the true remnant, namely to the Love, which is the moſt holy, which is kept and remained over, in heaven for an everlaſting reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, touching the ſins of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which convert and ſubmit them under the Love: The true moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through which moſt holy of the living Tabernacle of God, (namely, in his ſervice miniſtred under the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Love) the holy and the fore-front ſhall<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 8. b</note> be conſecrated and cleanſed again, the daily offering in the holy erected,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa 44.60, 61, 62, 65, 66. Ier. 33.30, 31, 33. Bar. 5. Eze. 36.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> builded and Sion comforted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall likewiſe find Grace before the Lord, and ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain the ſalvation alſo come again to his Land of inheritance and reſt, and the ſalvation ſhall be made manifeſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171452:24"/>
unto all people; To the end that the whole world might not be accurſed, like as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah;</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſ. 1.10. c Rom. 9. c.</note> but that there might yet a remnant be ſaved, and remain preſerved, even as the Lord hath ſpoken in times paſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When as now I had underſtood theſe things, I rejoyced me greatly, and my heart became glad, through the bountiful and entire love of God the Father, touching his great grace and mercie, to be ſhewed in the laſt time. Becauſe his rebuke and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement endureth<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 30. a Iſa. 54. a. 4 Mic. 7. b</note> but for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which cometh to an end: And for that his love, grace and mercy continueth for ever. And in that<note n="(f)" place="margin">Deut. 4. d</note> he forgetteth not his Covenant which<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ge. 12.13 17.22, 26.</note> he hath made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> for to gather, and to ſet up through his Love, his choſen people, <hi>Iſrael</hi> like as in times paſt, he hath promiſed and aſſured unto their Fathers, by<note n="(h)" place="margin">Luk. 1. g</note> the mouth of his holy Prophets.</p>
               <p n="6">6. With that I turned my face
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171452:25"/>
again to the moſt holy, and behold that ſame remained undefiled and was not<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ier. 17. b, Lam. 5. b</note> brought in deſolation. For <hi>Iſraels</hi> God who is a God of life, had hidden the ſame in heaven. And the heathen or uncircumciſed, which are captivated with manifold ignorances and errors, have not been therein at all; for<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 52. a Eze. 44. a</note> no uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed one can come or enter into the ſame ſanctuary, nor behold his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but it is reſerved and kept in ſtore for the Lords people <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Yea the ſame coſtly Treaſures, the Riches of God, the moſt precious and moſt pure beauty hath God kept for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to their ſalvation and<note n="(l)" place="margin">Iſa 60, 61. Ier. 31, 33. Eze. 36, 37.</note> joy in the laſt times, to the end to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the ſalvation of life,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Act. 12, a</note> out of the heavenly being or eſſential e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In which moſt holy there are likewiſe remained over all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious riches of God the Father, the unſpeakable Treaſure, which far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth all manner of garniſhing of beauty, namely<note n="(n)" place="margin">Exo 25. c Rom. 3. c Heb. 5 a</note> the mercy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171452:25"/>
ſeat prepared with the fine Gold; (which Seat continueth ſtanding for ever unmoveable) moreover the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ex. 25, 26. Apo. 12 a.</note> Ark of witneſs, wherein the Law of the Lord lieth, even as he<note n="(p)" place="margin">Deut. 9. b.</note> hath written the ſame with his own Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, (which continueth for ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken, unchangeable) And the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ex. 16. a Pſal. 68. Sapi 16. c Ioh. 6. d.</note> heavenly bread of life, even as God himſelf hath given the ſame from heaven unto his people to a ſatisfying their hunger, the which doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume or waſt away, but remaineth ever uncorruptible for evermore, for a witneſs unto poſterities that their fore-fathers were fed out of heaven with the ſame bread: There are yet in the ſame moſt holy, the manifold coſtly veſſels, of the moſt holy riches, every one of the moſt fine Gold. All theſe were ſtill remained over, in their perfect beauty, and not one of them was polluted or defiled.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But this ſumptuous garniſhing and all theſe riches of the Godly heavenly beauty, have been hidden a long time, for the wickedneſs cauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171452:26"/>
of the uncircumciſed, and they muſt alſo (inaſmuch as the iniquity grew on, even till<note n="(r)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 5, a 14. b. 15. a. Math. 24. b</note> ſhe was come to her full height, and had gotten the upper hand) neceſſarily remain hidden, becauſe they ſhould in the more beautious and glorious manner come to light and be revealed again, in the laſt time, namely when the iniquity of the uncircumciſed is even to her utter ending approached or come neer at hand.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Which iniquity ſhall now fall and periſh, through the revealing of theſe heavenly beauties; for God will with his Arm or ſtrength, and with the Arm of his Saints, and with all his ſumptuous garniſh, get the upper hand.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Wherewith he alſo ſheweth the juſt judgement of his Juſtice or righteouſneſs. For<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ier. 30.</note> the ungodly ſhall no more bear the dominion. And all whatſoever ſubmitteth not it ſelf under the Love, nor ſtandeth ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable thereunto, ſhall be rooted out, that they corrupt none, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171452:26"/>
marr the earrh, any more.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But the Love ſhall flouriſh<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15</note> everlaſtingly in her ſervice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the Lords people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which he himſelf hath choſen for his<note n="(u)" place="margin">Deut. 4. c 32. a Iſa. 19. c Ier. 51. c.</note> own heritage, as likewiſe all good willing ones, which ſtand ſubmitted under the obedience of the Love, may be comforted: and ſo may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold everlaſtingly, the goodneſs or loving kindneſs of God his Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended through his love: which boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful goodneſs, the God of life hath foreſeen to accompliſh upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even as he in times paſt hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame by <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſervant, and by the mouth of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:171452:27"/>
               <head>The fifth Chapter.</head>
               <p>ALthough now that the Levites, the Prieſts, the Prophets or Preachers, and alſo the people are all fallen or eſtranged from the true God-ſervice, and that the daily offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hath ceaſed for a long time, and the holy of the Tabernacle of God layn utterly waſte, with abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of deſolation, yet<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ier 17. b Lam. 5 b</note> is the moſt holy notwithſtanding remained over pure and unſpotted, and the high Prieſt<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 5 b 7. b 8 a 9 c</note> which continueth a Prieſt for ever, is alſo found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, for he hath ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtedfaſt, in his mercy ſeat in the moſt holy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are all ſhrunk away<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſa. 14. a 53. a. Rom. 3. b.</note> and changed themſelves, there is not one remained ſtanding, or righteous, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171452:27"/>
are all turned away, either to the right or to the left ſide, and many by reaſon of their ignorance, have born the ſtrange yoakes of the beautified God ſervices.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But this everlaſting Prieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſtedfaſt like a ſtony Rock, whoſe feat endureth from<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſa. 45. a Heb. 1. a.</note> ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting to everlaſting, as a perpetual Saviour, to an eternal curing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement, for the ſins of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for his God hath annointed him to be an high Prieſt and a true Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwixt God and man, and to<note n="(e)" place="margin">He. 7.8. a 9. a. b. c.</note> be an everlaſting Miniſter, of the ſpiritual and heavenly goodneſs, to the end he might ſave the poor and miſerable man, who through ſins or offences lieth be wrapped in the death, and to make him alive through him: and to ſet him up again<note n="(f)" place="margin">Rom 8. b</note> out of the death.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In which ſpiritual and heavenly ſervice, miniſtred under the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Love, the holy becometh conſecrated again by the ſame high Prieſt, namely<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Heb. 9 b.</note> the ſprinkling of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171452:28"/>
his own blood for an everlaſting Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and ſo it is all waſhed and ſanctified or cleanſed through his blood.</p>
               <p n="5">5, That verily is the Goſpel of the Kingdom of God and Chriſt, and the New Teſtament,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mar. 16. b Apo. 14. a.</note> that ſame was alſo publiſhed in times paſt, for an everlaſting forgiveneſs of ſins un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thoſe that believe thereon.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Behold this high Prieſt is the life everlaſting, which was with the Father of life in the beginning, and is revealed unto us in the heaven, (namely in the boſom of his Father) and we<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ioh. 1. b.</note> do behold his glory, even a glory as the only born Son of the Father, full of grace and truth.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We do witneſs alſo, that he is the true Meſſiah, or Chriſt, which was preached in the World in times paſt, and likewiſe publiſhed of him in his coming,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 9 a. Luk. 1. d.</note> that he ſhould be a King or Prince over the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> for ever: of whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alſo there ſhall be no end.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He is a Saviour to all people that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171452:28"/>
believe on him: And the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Act. 4.10. c.</note> ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, or cometh only by him, and by none other, neither in heaven, nor yet upon the earth; for he is<note n="(m)" place="margin">Rom. 8 10. Iſa. 13. a. b. 1 Pet. 2. c.</note> the end or the accompliſhment of the Law, upon whom all the Prophets of God have witneſſed from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in glory like as is written of him.</p>
               <p n="9">9. He it is<note n="(n)" place="margin">Iſ. 13. a. b 1 Per. 2. c.</note> which ſuffereth for our ſins cauſe in the holy, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our ſins, and ſo hath like<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ioh. 10. b</note> a faithful Shepherd, given over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſame holy to be an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſin, whereby<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Pe. 4. a</note> to draw and arm us to the ſame mind, and ſo we to offer up our ſins through the daily offering in the holy, and to burn the ſame upon his holy Altar; The which is his croſs or patience in the holy.</p>
               <p n="10">10. So even thus doth Chriſt through himſelf (namely through<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rom. 9. a Eph. 2. a. Col. 1 c. 2. b.</note> the incorporating us into his death of the Croſs) prepare the life and peace for us, making us free, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171452:29"/>
waſhing<note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 10. c.</note> us from the evil conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And ſo we obtain through him in that manner, a free entrance into the holy, for to accompliſh the God-ſervice in the holy, &amp; to inherit the abundant riches of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the everlaſting life: The which cometh unto us plentifully, and appeareth in cleerneſs, if that we for our parts, do<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mat. 16. c Luk. 9.14. c</note> daily take up our Croſs with Chriſt, follow after him in the holy, and ſo become<note n="(u)" place="margin">Rom. 6 a</note> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in his death,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.5.8. a.</note> to be an offering for the ſin, whereby to be<note n="(x)" place="margin">Col. 2. b.</note> juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ſin, through Faith, &amp; that meerly by Grace, &amp; not by Works.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Behold ſuch a manner of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and daily God-ſervice in the holy, is no doubt very convenient for us to uſe and perform. For ſo then, namely in the performance of the daily offering or God-ſervice in the holy, there appeareth or cometh to us in the ſpirit, the ſpiritual high Prieſt or Chriſt, according to the Spirit, who is not of this earth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of fleſh and blood, but of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171452:29"/>
heavenly God-head; &amp; the ſame high<note n="(y)" place="margin">Heb. 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> Prieſt, is alſo very needful for us, becauſe he is faithful, and remaineth for ever.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whoſe ſervice or high Prieſts office, is not outward according to the manner of the foregoing ſervice of the Elders, adminiſtred among the unregenerate or unrenwed men, as in the letter, and with the letter, or with ſpeakable words, but his ſervice cometh to paſs in the new birth of the inward ſpiritual and heavenly man.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Heb. 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> with the miniſtration of the ſpiritual and heavenly goods, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſpiritual and heavenly Prieſt-office,</p>
               <p n="13">13. And to that end, (namely to bring men to the new birth of the inward ſpiritual heavenly man) have the outward miniſtrations of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the foregoing with the man,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal 3. c. 4, 5 a</note> under the which, he to the training up of him in all good nurture and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is kept and taught, even unto the new birth in Jeſus Chriſt: through the which, he doth then likewiſe live,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171452:30"/>
and walk in<note n="(b)" place="margin">Luk. 1. g.</note> all upright righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, both inwardly before God, and outwardly among men: and to ſuch an upright<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. a. Titus 3. b.</note> birth, or the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſervices or adminiſtrations of the Godly teſtimonies of the holy Spirit of Love, a foregoing office, or<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Co. 3. a</note> light unto the man, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, declareth and holdeth forth the godlineſs unto him as in a Glaſs. And ſo then the man, if he believe the requiring of the fore-going ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and deſire to ſtand obedient thereunto, becometh prepared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to the ſame godlineſs, and taught to the Kingdom of heaven. And that is the ſame miniſtration, which<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gal 3 c 4. a. Heb. 7. b.</note> reacheth to the ſpiritual and true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Jeſus Chriſt. And it is the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Prieſts office, of the Elders of the holy underſtanding, which in its office or ſervice, hath the foregoing to the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. a. 1 Cor. 4. b. Gal. 4. b.</note> new birth in Jeſus Chriſt, as is already ſaid; which ſervices are all witneſſes and directions, unto the very true and ſpiritual office in the Spirit: And although the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171452:30"/>
being miniſtred in the letter, and through the letter or ſerviceable word, do bring<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Co. 3. b</note> a great illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and clearneſs, unto the unil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated ones, yet are thoſe ſame for all that no more but a ſerviceable ſhaddow, proceeding from the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and heavenly ſervice of the great glory and cleerneſs of Chriſt, in the inward being and form.</p>
               <p n="14">14. For Chriſt according to the Spirit hath<note n="(h)" place="margin">Heb. 3.8.9. a.</note> an higher function, or office, or a more excellent ſervice, and a greater ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or clearneſs, then hath all fleſh and blood, writing, letters, or ſpeakable words. For he is a Miniſter, or an high Prieſt in the Spirit,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 8 a. 9. a. b. c.</note> as a Miniſter of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and heavenly goods, as is before ſaid. For he himſelf is the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb 1. a.</note> right heir, in all the riches of God his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Almighty Father.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Behold this high Prieſt is ſpirit and life, the true<note n="(l)" place="margin">Iſa. 9. a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> King and a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord, a peaceable prince: And not this or that without us: But he<note n="(m)" place="margin">Act. 17. c</note> is in us all which believe on him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171452:31"/>
to the truth: And we all which abide ſtedfaſt in the faith, have the life through him, who is neither unfaithful, nor falling away like unto a man. For he doth not ſhrink nor fall away either from us, or from his Father, but through the Love<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat. 28. c Ioh. 14 b.</note> continueth with us, and with his Father for ever.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Alſo he is not changeable, in his office or miniſtration, like as are the children of men: who do one while ſetup one thing for an obedience, or for a God-ſervice, and that altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without the ſervice of Chriſt and his Love; and then again ſome other thing, which directeth not to the true life of Chriſt, nor unto the upright being of his Love.</p>
               <p n="17">17. But his ſervice, will, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, is both now preſently, and at all times, like as it was in the beginning, and it ſhall ſo remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable for evermore. For his Commandment, Will, and Precept, is<note n="(o)" place="margin">Da. 6.10 Math 22. d Ioh 15 b. 1 Tim. 1. a</note> nothing elſe but the love and the life of godlineſs: And that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171452:31"/>
is the old commandment from the beginning:<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ioh. 2. a</note> And it is the new commandment, as being for to come, or for to be made manifeſt in this ſame laſt time, in the obedience of the requiring of the ſervice of Love.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Therefore ſeeing now that this high Prieſt, which is inviſible, but yet is known in the ſpirit, hath ſuch an unchangeable commandment or ſervice among us, in the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſervice of his Love: So ſtandeth he likewiſe firm and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable towards us in the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to an everlaſting reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our ſins, as a true<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Tim. 2 a Heb. 9. b</note> mediator betwixt God and us.</p>
               <p n="19">19. He himſelf alſo is partaker with us in ſuffering, touching<note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 2. b 5. a.</note> our griefs, and purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in his ſervice of Love, through himſelf, and through none other, or any other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:171452:32"/>20. Therefore hath God like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſworn unto him,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſa. 100. Heb. 7. c.</note> and it ſhall not repent him) that he ſhall continue a Prieſt for ever. They<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſa. 102. Iſa. 51. a. Heb. 1. b</note> ſhall all become old, and become changed like a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 45 Heb. 1. a.</note> his ſeat (as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) endureth and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from everlaſting to everlaſting: it is very true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:171452:32"/>
               <head>The ſixth Chapter.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch now as that that God which dwelleth in the heavens, is through his bountiful Love, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing of the holy things unto us, out of an heavenly revelation in his ſervice of Love; therefore have we the more aſſured confidence on the ſame ſervice of Love: which very true ſervice is now in the laſt time come unto us for to miniſter, to a bleſſing and ſalvation of thoſe men, which are good of will, to the end that they ſhould all aſſemble them thereto. For the love in her ſervice, is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 24. Luk. 17. d.</note> bait or prey whereunto the Eagles ſhall reſort and aſſemble, and that to a unity in one band of the Love.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For it ſhall now, whatſoever in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171452:33"/>
the Love loveth the peace and the righteouſneſs, aſſemble or come to the ſervice of the Love, and concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably incline them unto the ſame; for it is unpoſſible that it ſhould bide back: but that in thoſe dayes it ſhall all (namely, all whatſoever loveth righteouſneſs, and hath intended peace and love) joyn it ſelf to one, and not refuſe to have or uſe the unity in the Love with us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Seeing that all my longing ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth towards the ſame, therefore hath my heart ſeldom any reſt, by reaſon of my longing towards the ſame and for that the godly Baite (namely the right and true ſervice of Love) might have his miniſtration and declaring everywhere, whereby all Eagles, which hunger and thiriſt thereafter, might aſſemble them thereto. For thereunto doubtleſs, ſhall all thoſe which love or ſtand affected unto righteouſneſs, become aſſembled and comprehended, or knit in one Band of the Love with us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They ſhall alſo give themſelves
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171452:33"/>
thereunto good-willingly, if they do but hear of ſuch an aſſembling, and unity in the Love, and that ſee into, know and Credit the ſame, let them be whereſoever they are, or whoſoever they be, whether the Jews, Chriſtians or Mahometans, heathen or of what generations, nations, ſects, factions, or religions ſoever they be; they ſhall all mutually, for the righteouſneſs and peaces cauſe, ſubmit themſelves with us under the Love. Becauſe that they might every one be incorporated to the upright<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 11. b</note> ſtock of life, to the laud and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eph. 1. b.</note> praiſe of the glory of the living God.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Which glory of God, God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for himſelf now in the laſt time in the ſervice of his love, to the ſpreading abroad of his great name,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mal. 1. b</note> for that his holy name may be known and magnified univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Before, or in the preſence of which ſervice of Love,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 31. b</note> all blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous tongues muſt become dumb, all wickedneſs grow aſhamed,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171452:34"/>
and all pride ſubmit it ſelf, to the end that all that feareth God, loveth his Promiſes and hopeth thereon, may allow of or conſent unto the office or ſervice of Love, and aſſemble them to the Concord of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For the ſervice of love only ſhall flouriſh, under the which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all underſtanding ſhall to an obeying of the requiring of the ſaid ſervice of Love, give it ſelf<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Cor. 10. a.</note> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to an unity of peace, and to an incorporating unto the vertues in all Love.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Through which diſcerning, of the upright and true ſe vice, and of the aſſembling of the upright hearts to the ſame, I have figured forth, or witneſſed with theſe preſent writings and teſtimonies, the true Tabernacle of God, and his ſervices miniſtred under the obedience of the Love of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the life, (even as the ſame is by Gods grace revealed unto me) becauſe that we might all of us, according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171452:34"/>
come to that<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 12. a</note> one manner of God-ſervice of<note n="(h)" place="margin">Luk. 1. g.</note> upright righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egardeth: alſo that all people which according to the ſpirit are<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eph. 2 4.</note> ſtrangers and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant touching the true God and his ſervice, might look into the ſame, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo come to<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Tim. 2 a.</note> the knowledge of the truth, and be converted to the Love and her ſervice, whereby to walk in all love,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eph. 4. a.</note> as children of peace, and as peaceable brethren.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But not in miſnurter and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlineſs, according to the manner of the uncircumciſed heathen, nor in contention through ſelf-wiſdom, or Scripture-learnedneſs, nor yet in diſputing concerning the circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or baptiſm, but in all diſcreetneſs and orderlyneſs of the upright life, according to the true circumciſion,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ier. 4 a Rom. 2. c Phil 3. a Col. 2. b.</note> which cometh to paſs in the heart (the which is in laying away of the ſin in the fleſh) and according to the true baptiſm of the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Math. 3. b Rom. 6. a Col. 2. b.</note> holy Ghoſt, which cometh to paſs in the ſpirit, in a new life, of the true
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171452:35"/>
minde, full of all Love.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Therefore reſpect now well the upright Judgement in your hearts. For all hearts ſhall now in this laſt time<note n="(p)" place="margin">Luk. 2. d</note> become mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. There ſhall alſo be found but one manner of heathen-ſhip, foreskin or uncircumciſion. And all hearts of the heathen or uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, being without <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Gods ſanctuary, and without the commonalty of Iſrael, or of Chriſt, (let them then hold what God-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices they will) ſhall through the foreskin of the ſinful fleſh, appear manifeſtly to be uncircumciſed, and to ſtand captivated with the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient knowledge<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſa. 52. a Eze. 44 b</note>. Of ſuch uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed ones there ſhall not one come into the ſanctuary.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In like manner, there ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be found but one manner of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Baptiſm,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 56. a Eze. 37. c. Ioh. 10. b</note> and houſe of Iſrael or Chriſt; and all the Saints or holy ones of God, that are of the houſe of Iſrael or Chriſt, ſhall walk
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171452:35"/>
under the obedience of the Love, and have their fellowſhip with us within <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Apo. 21. a</note> holy City of God from heaven.</p>
               <p n="13">13. And the ſame likewiſe ſhall be one manner of Tabernacle of God, or houſe of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Gods light,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Apo. 21. c Iſa. 60.</note> yea he himſelf ſhineth as a light and cleerneſs unto his people Iſrael, becauſe that they all may even free without anguiſh, and without fear walk peaceably in his light.</p>
               <p n="14">14. From whoſe hearts<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 25 a 2 Cor. 3 b</note> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin of the ſinful fleſh, and of the diſobedient darkneſſes ſhall be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; for the light that ariſeth over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> according to the promiſes,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſ. 60 a. c</note> ſhall ſhine about them all. Whereunto likewiſe all people that have a luſt to Iſraels God, and to his Law, ſtatutes and rights,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 2. a 11. b. 13. c. Mich. 4. a Zach. 8 c.</note> ſhall be aſſembled, and offer or bring unto the glorious God in his holy Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, oblations and gifts,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſ 5, 6. a Ier. 33. c Eze. 20 a Mal. 1 b. 3. c. Rom 12. a</note> which are acceptable unto him, according to the ſame manner, like as in times
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171452:36"/>
paſt, God hath ſhewed and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſame unto <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſervant.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Which holy Tabernacle of God with his fore-front, holy, and moſt holy, together with his God-ſervices, of the Levitical Prieſts and ſacrifices, and the ſervice of the high Prieſts office, God hath in times paſt, ſet forth figuratively unto the people of Iſrael by<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex. 25, 26, 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 35, 40.</note> the ſervice of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> or figured forth the ſame as ſhadows of the true being or ſubſtance of the ſpiritual or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly goods, which were revealed or ſhewed unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> to the end<note n="(b)" place="margin">Exo. 19, 20 a. Deut. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Pſal. 50. b. Jer. 7. c. Zach. 7. a. b.</note> that they ſhould never more forget the being of the ſame, but continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember it, and in the obedience of the commandments and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Lord, ſhould wax zealous, and proceed on after the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:171452:36"/>
               <head>The ſeventh Chapter.</head>
               <p>BUT when the people of Iſrael did cleave or incline with their hearts wholly to the Figures, Images or ſhadows, and accepted and uſed the ſame for the upright God-ſervice it ſelf, in ſuch ſort as though God required the Images or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and that they were not chiefly and above all inclined to the upright being of Chriſt it ſelf, which yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God requireth thereby (wherein alſo the Figures, Images and Shadows do point) therefore hath God liked or allowed of none of their ſervices,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal 50, 51. b. Iſa. 1. b. 59. c. 66. a. Ier. 6.7. c. Mic. 6. a Zach. 7. a Mal. 1. a</note> neither have they likewiſe pleaſed him, but have rather been unto him a loathſomneſs, and an utter miſliking.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore hath God alſo had
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171452:37"/>
no luſt or pleaſure unto ſuch people, becauſe they ſerved the Images and Figures, and not their Lord their God only according to the truth, like as it ſtandeth commanded in the Law of the Lord, and is required by the Figures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which abuſe towards the Images and Shadows, God hath oftentimes rebuked, and witneſſed unto them by the mouth of his holy Prophets,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eze. 14. a Zac. 14. a</note> that they ſhould turn them unto the Lord their God, from thoſe ſame Images, and thoſe their abominations, whom they ſerved with the delight of their hearts, againſt the requiring of the Law.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Even thus hath God many times, by his ſervants the Prophets, required the fruits of the Law, and the outward form and obſervation thereof, which many could not diſtinct or divide aſunder.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But ſeeing they were bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Images and Figures, and blinded by them, through their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (which blindneſs was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171452:37"/>
of the heart) ſo have they by that occaſion looked into, or eſteemed the ſervices of the Images or Figures to be Gods requiring, or to be the true God-ſervice it ſelf, and have accounted Gods Prophets, that pointed upon the very truth, or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelf which was required, to<note n="(c)" place="margin">3 Ki. 22. c Ier. 8. a. 20: a 26. b. 32. a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> be falſe, and many times have put them<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Par. 29. c. Math. 23. d</note> to death.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Although they ſuppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves now to be Gods ſervants, or to uſe and maintain the true God-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: yet were they notwithſtanding in that their falſe uſe, the very right Idol-ſervices, obſerving the God-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices falſly.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Even ſo goeth it likewiſe with all thoſe which look into, or eſteem the outward God-ſervices, or the outward obedience, for the true being or real ſubſtance it ſelf, alſo do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter the ſame in that manner, and ſo go on therewith, and do not through thoſe ſame, or by their means turn them in the Spirit unto Almighty God.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171452:38"/>8. Seeing now that the God of life doth not require the Images, Shadows, or Figures by the Law, but that which is the living, being or ſubſtance it ſelf; therefore hath he alſo at the laſt, out of the grace of his Love, which continueth for ever, revealed<note n="(e)" place="margin">Act 2. a</note> the true being through his Chriſt, unto his people Iſrael, like as the ſame was required by the Law, and by the Images, Figures, and Shadows, ſhewing cleerly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereby what is his will, even as he had in times paſt, through the ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and his Prophets both required it, and alſo as being to come, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame. In which time of the heavenly Revelation, and of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual birth or generation of God, according to the Spirit, many in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael rejoyced them.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Seeing now, that the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead was come to the houſe of Iſrael, as that God raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up unto them his Chriſt,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Act. 2 d. 3. b 10. c. 13. d 1 Cor. 15.</note> as the firſtling riſen from death, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did many in thoſe dayes hope
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171452:38"/>
upon the comfort of Iſrael, or<note n="(g)" place="margin">Act. 1.</note> their reſtoring and ſetting up, even as God had fore-ſpoken the ſame by his Prophet<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ezek. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. But the God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who forſaketh not his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſrael, neither forgetteth the ſame Covenant that<note n="(i)" place="margin">Deut. 4. Luk. 1. g.</note> he made with their Fathers, hath preſerved or kept in his own ſecretneſs the time of his wonderful Works, and the mercy towards the dead of the houſe of Iſrael.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For in thoſe dayes many in Iſrael underſtood not the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works of God, nor yet the Grace towards ſalvation, that was opened or come unto them; But they became blinded, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from the ſame and knew or underſtood not in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the reſtoring or ſetting up of Iſrael was to come to paſs; For God had ſtayed or reſerved the ſame reſtoring, becauſe he would in the laſt time, through
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171452:39"/>
the ſame, make<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mal. 1. a</note> his holy name known, glorious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned among all the heathen, or people, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and ſo to<note n="(l)" place="margin">Iſa. 11. b Luk. 2. d</note> reveal to his people Iſrael his Love, the Banner of true Righteouſneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:171452:39"/>
               <head>The eighth Chapter.</head>
               <p>FOR which cauſe ſake, the grace of ſalvation, which was opened or come unto them from out of God, and the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ioh. 1. a 1 Ioh. 1. a</note> light and life, which was the Father, and which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in Iſrael for a Chriſt of God, was publiſhed, or preached unto all people, for a witneſs of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead, and for a Goſpel, or a joyful Meſſage of the Kingdom. And moreover the Kingdom of the God of heaven became manifeſt in Iſrael, and was witneſſed both among them, and at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> as namely that that which they heard and ſaw, whenas the fiftieth day was fulfilled, were the wonderful Works of God, whereof <hi>Ioel</hi> the Prophet had ſpoken before,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioel 2. c Act. 2.</note> and it ſhall come to paſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171452:40"/>
ſaith God in the laſt dayes, when the end of the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk. 21.</note> ſuppreſſion of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is come, and the fulneſs of the heathen is come in or performed,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa 59. c Rom. 17.</note> becauſe that all Iſrael in that ſort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſaved, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wherein God now ſheweth, that he is not forgetful of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as he hath<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 12, 13, 15, 17, 21, 22.</note> made the ſame with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and that he is a God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of his ſeed for evermore; Through whom he hath in times paſt made known his holy name, and will alſo in the laſt time make it known therethrough, according to the Promiſes. And they ſhall effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perceive that<note n="(f)" place="margin">Deut. 3. d Iſa. 43, 44, 45, 48.</note> he the God of Iſrael is only the Lord, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him there is no God more and that all heathen that fear not the ſame God, nor yet do learn to keep his Laws, Statutes, and Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, are an ignorant people, without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, even as hitherto it hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, among many multitudes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171452:40"/>
or heathen, who through their own wiſdom (how ingenious and through-lighted or cleer of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſoever they have been) have<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. b.</note> not known or underſtood Gods holy wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore hath it pleaſed God to<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 29. 1 Cor. 1. b</note> ſhame the world in her wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to incompaſs or go beyond all choſen religions, in their ſelf-framed holyneſs, and to ſave his people through himſelf, becauſe he would eſtabliſh them all in his Love, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Temple for his holy dwelling: In the which<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Cor 3. Heb. 1. a</note> God doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his beſt beloved whom he hath alwayes loved from the beginning; namely the very<note n="(k)" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. Col. 1. b</note> like being of his God-head, the which the God of life hath formed in the man from the beginning.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But alaſs this ſame is unknown unto many, or they are by reaſon<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gen. 3. a.</note> of their fall and eſtranging from God, ſo covered with the darkneſſes, that they cannot, according to the ſpirit of the inward man, behold the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171452:41"/>
being, or real form of their God. But when as the man, through the hearing and believing of the gracious word turneth him in the ſpirit<note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. b. 4. a</note> unto God, then becometh the fore-skin of his fleſh, or the covering of the ſin put off from his heart. For<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ioh. 4 b 8. c. 14. a.</note> God is a Spirit, a Light, or a Life, and is not otherwiſe known and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, but in his own ſpirit, light and life.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Now when the man turneth him (as aforeſaid) thereunto, under the obedience of his gracious Word, and ſervice of Love, the ſame like being cometh unto him in the ſpirit; then<note n="(o)" place="margin">Eph. 5. b</note> is the Image of God raiſed up in him, and awakened unto him in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That ſame verily is the life, whereof the Kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> hath ſpoken in time paſt, where he ſaith,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſa. 17. b</note> I will behold thy face in righteouſneſs, I will be ſatisfied when thine Image awaketh.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When the man turneth himſelf in the ſpirit,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Eze 18 d. Ioel 2. b.</note> unto God, as alſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171452:41"/>
humbleth himſelf with all his heart, to the holy and gracious Word, and is good of will to the obeying of the requiring of his ſervice of Love, then appeareth to him the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Lev. 10. b Eze. 44. c</note> holy and unholy.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now when the man turneth himſelf away from the unholy of the uncircumciſed hearts, and turneth him obediently to the holy, or to Gods ſanctuary of all God-fearing and circumciſed hearts, and wholly gives himſelf to enter into the ſame, and that ſo<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 1. a Eccl. 1. b. 2. a</note> the fear of the higheſt God gets a ſhape in him; then doth the right departing out from all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſhneſs, and the entrance into the forefront of the true Tabernacle of God come to paſs even there with the ſame man. For he goeth out of the uncircumciſion into the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Ier. 4 a</note> foreskin of his heart: and receiveth in that ſort, through the ſervice of the holy and gracious Word, Gods Covenant of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the fleſh.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In which ſervice of the holy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171452:42"/>
and gracious Word, miniſtred in the fear of God, the fore-skin or cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the darkneſſes wherewith all heathen are cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or grown uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed,<note place="margin">The true fore-front of the holy and true Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God, is the turning unto God in the fear of God, and ſo through the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the holy and gracious word, to ſeparate ones ſelf from all heatheniſh miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurture, or to turn away or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe ones heart from all wickedneſs, which fore-front in his ſervice, is the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the right dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the holy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, and betwixt the circumciſed ones, the Lords people, and the uncircumciſed, or heathen.</note> is<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 25. 2 Cor. 3.</note> put off. The which is the laying away of the<note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.4. a. Heb. 12. a</note> ſin in the fleſh, whereby to ſhew due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, according to the Law of the Lord, namely to fear God upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to deſire the good with fervency of heart, and to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe or purge the heart, and all whatſoever is man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The which is<note n="(y)" place="margin">Rom. 2. Phil. 3. Col. 2. b</note> the true circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth</p>
               <p n="10">10. Finally that ſame is the fore-front
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171452:42"/>
of the true Tabernacle of God: and the right difference<note n="(z)" place="margin">Lev. 10. b Eze. 44.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed heathen. Betwixt thoſe that fear God, and are good of will, and thoſe that fear not God, and are evil of will, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Jer. 7. c. 11. a. 13, 18.</note> ſo live according to the ſenſuality or ſelf-mindedneſs of their own deſires, or according to all manner of light-mindedneſs; as that are without rule, looſe, unbridled, or wilde of heart, and do neither love nor obtain any wiſdom, nor any holy knowledge; whoſe hearts take hold of nothing elſe but all manner of filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But through the fear<note n="(b)" place="margin">Prov. 1. a Eccl. 1. c. 2. a</note> of God, by means of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the heart, through the good will, the man cometh to the godly wiſdom, and holy knowledge,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171452:43"/>
and ſo the fear of God driveth him to turn away<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 8. a</note> from the ſin. And then proceeding forward, even to the holy he becometh juſtified from the ſin through the Faith, in the daily taking<note n="(d)" place="margin">Lu. 9 14. c</note> up of his Croſs, in like ſuffering with Chriſt, till unto<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 6. a. 8. b.</note> the death of the ſin, which is the daily offering in the holy.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But now when the man is turned<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eccl. 2. a</note> unto God with a good will, in Godly fear, and under the obedience of the Love is cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled or joyned to a Commonalty of the Saints of God, then is he departed out of the heathenſhip, and hath at that time his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation or fellowſhip with the adminiſtration and diſcipline of the holy Word, miniſtred betwixt the fore-front and the Altar of the holy offering, till that his offering and gift be (through Faith) begun or taken in hand, in the holy for a burnt offering;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171452:43"/>
through which burning of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering upon the holy Altar of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the holy,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 57. b Eph. 2. b</note> the Peace betwixt the man and God the Father is prepared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171452:44"/>
               <head>The ninth Chapter.</head>
               <p>BUT for as much as this true God-ſervice in the holy, is not yet (according to the inward man in the ſpirit) known unto every one, nor underſtood according to the truth, and we do find many young and little ones of underſtanding, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny feeble and weak ones, and many uncertain conſciences: all which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding do ſtand bent and well-minded, with a good will towards the Love, and towards the holy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. So is therefore the life of righteouſneſs evidently witneſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them out of the ſervice of Love, which teſtimonies of the truth, are likewiſe adminiſtred unto them through Doctrines, ſpeakable words, or with writing, (namely, unto thoſe that have turned from the heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſo endeavour them to the obeying of the word and his ſervice, and which do fear God) with which ſervice, there is required of them,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171452:44"/>
the obedience to the Love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal 3. c 4. a. Heb. 7. b.</note> to a ſuſtaining of them, whereout ſome better thing is yet to be hoped for.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſame is verily the daily God-ſervice, which is well pleaſing unto the Lord, and the upright Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which be miniſtred before the Lord, unto the God-fearing hearts, by the Miniſters of the holy word.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which Miniſters with the ſame ſervice of the gracious and holy word, is the Levitical Prieſts office, wherethrough the ſlain-offering is prepared before<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 33. b</note> the Lord, among the little-ones, and ſinners, who bear ſorrow and grief for the ſins cauſe; alſo the burnt-offering is begun, and daily uſed, &amp; the meat offering like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe kindled and offered up.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Which ſervice likewiſe of the Levitical Prieſts office al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtands or continues before the Lord, in the ſervice of his Love, as a mutual aſſiſtance and ſtrengthening for the little or weak ones: and that altogether in the Love to the ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the Congregations, for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171452:45"/>
the ſins of the ignorant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Which ſervice of the Levitical Prieſts office, God would not have required, if the man had not fallen into the ſin, but had ſtill walked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly in the light of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But foraſmuch as it hath not gone ſo with the man, therefore hath God, even of neceſſity, added the ſame ſervice unto his promiſes, for to inform therewith the unilluminated ones, the infirm, weak, and young ones, or little ones of underſtanding, who do yet oftentimes ſin, and are of little growth in Faith, and ſo to aſſiſt and ſerve them therewith for a certain time, betwixt the fore-front and the Altar, for an entrance unto them in the holy, &amp; to bring unto the high or great God of heaven,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſa. 11. d Iſa 56 a Mal. 1. b Rom. 11. a</note> ſuch an offering as is delightful unto him.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Even thus become they all converted or turned away from the ſin, and ſuccoured or trayned up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſervice of the Love, to the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Luk. 1. g Eph. 1. a</note> knowledge of the upright life of the Juſt, to the end, that they may all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one, even as of one mind<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ioh. 17 c</note> in the Love.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171452:45"/>8. Now when one doth know the ſame life, according to ſuch an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſervice and nature of the Love, and is grown believing towards the ſame, then is there revealed and brought in the ſpirit unto the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, the boldneſs to enter into the holy, for to accompliſh the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and his requiring in the holy, like as God is requiring the ſame accompliſhment by the Law and the Prophets, and by the ſervice of the Elders in the holy underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which accompliſhment in the holy, is our offering in the offering of Chriſt, through his<note n="(g)" place="margin">He. 9. b.c</note> blood, which prepareth for us a new and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way.</p>
               <p n="9">9, Behold that is the true God-ſervice, through Chriſt in the holy, which is now by Gods grace opened and brought unto us, to the end to ſet up the righteouſneſs in the ſame through Faith, which is required by the Law and Ordinance of the Lord. For whatſoever is<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rom 8. a</note> unpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the Law to do through
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171452:46"/>
works, that ſame is accompliſhed in Chriſt through Faith: whereby Chriſt is in that manner the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the Law: and erecteth the upright righteouſneſs among his Believers, and eſtabliſheth them in the ſame.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Therefore Chriſt is no breaker, but a fulfiller of the Law: for<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 3. b</note> Chriſt came not to make void, or break the Law and the Prophets, but to perform them, becauſe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that is of value before God, may be made manifeſt through his light, to an everlaſting eſtabliſhment of the promiſes of God made unto the Fathers, whereby to waſh and cleanſe the man from his ſpotted or<note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb. 9. b</note> evil conſcience, that he might laud God with peace and joy.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But this daily God-ſervice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the front and the Altar in the holy which is prepared and miniſtred by the ſervice of the holy and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Word, and by the Prieſts office out of <hi>Levy,</hi> or by the Elders in the holy underſtanding, is the ſervice
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171452:46"/>
which God hath added to his<note n="(l)" place="margin">Rom. 4. b 5. c. 7. a.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> to a ſtrengthening of the belief extending to the Promiſes; Becauſe the man ſhould with a good courage in the good and godly life of righteouſneſs, among the Elders in the holy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Eph. 1. b 1 Pet. 2. a</note> grow up therein to an eſtabliſhing of the Promiſes of God the Father.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In ſuch manner doubtleſs is the ſame ſervice of the holy Word, which is adminiſtred by the Elders in the holy underſtanding under the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Love, very profitable and furtherſome for the good-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs, the while they<note n="(n)" place="margin">Gal. 4. a.</note> are yet little or young in the godly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: And for thoſe that like unto children, ſtand ſimply ſubmitted under the Love, to the end that no man ſhould err, through any igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, nor tye his heart to the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his own ſpirit, but only have regard unto the ſervice of Love, to the obeying his requiring until that the daily God-ſervice in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171452:47"/>
be begun with him, and have his full courſe with him; Alſo till the true<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. b</note> light come unto him, and the day likewiſe appear from on high, or as a cleerneſs of the morning ſtar ariſe in his heart, and that the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ioh. 1. a</note> life be come unto him in the ſpirit, according to the truth, and have<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. Gal. 4. b</note> a ſhape in him, as a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God or of Chriſt, which is the upright being, or real form it ſelf, full of all Love.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Till unto this ſame day (namely till that the light of life, as a true being, an upright righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be come unto the man) doth the daily God-ſervice for the ſins cauſe endure in the holy; ſo long alſo<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Co. 3. b</note> remaineth the vail before the moſt holy, namely till the holy be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or miniſtred in his full courſe of miniſtration, with upright daily oblations, which are acceptable unto God.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But this daily offering, or gift which the man is Debtor to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, in the holy, or that wherein God
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171452:47"/>
hath a pleaſure, is not alone the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; for God hath<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſ. 40.50.</note> never willed nor required the ſame without the good will of the heart.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Therefore it is a ſpiritual offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, proceeding out of<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 11. c Iſa. 57.66.</note> a lowly and humble heart, and the beginning of the ſame upright offering ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth even thus, in every man that is good-willing towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his righteouſneſs,</p>
               <p n="16">16. O God I come, and have a luſt to<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſa. 40. a Heb. 10. a</note> do thy will.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Now when the man findeth himſelf thus minded, and deſireth to enter into the ſervice of Love, and his requiring, in this ſort is his heart pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and altogether become willing to<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat. 16. c Luk 9.14. c</note> take up his Croſs, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to follow after the<note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. c</note> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified and killed Jeſus Chriſt, in the belief, under the obedience of his love, till unto his death, (even the death of the Croſs)<note n="(z)" place="margin">Rom. 6. Col. 2. b.</note> and to be baptized into the ſame death, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to enter even ſo into the life, out of the deadly ſin,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. a Rom. 6.8. b 2 Cor. 4.</note> through the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171452:48"/>
ſecond birth, from death. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through he is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made free,<note place="margin">The true holy, of the holy and true Tabernacle of God, is the belief tending to the mortifying of the ſin, in the after following of Chriſt, till unto the ſecond birth from the death, (the which is the willing obedience of the belief) which holy and his ſervice, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in the belief, wherein the death of the ſin cometh to paſs, is the very true holy, and the right difference between the moſt holy and the fore-front.</note> or delivered from all chooſing of this or that according to his own will or pleaſure, ſaying with his whole heart;</p>
               <p n="18">18. O GOD,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Act. 9 a</note> WHAT wilt thou have me to do?</p>
               <p n="19">19. Behold in ſuch a mind, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or inclination to the obedience of the belief, and to continue<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eccl. 2. a Math. 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſtedfaſt therein till unto the death, and to the new birth from the death, conſiſteth the mans conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171452:48"/>
to his God: and he becometh ſo clean turned about from his ſelfneſs, that he is like unto<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 18. a 1 Pet. 2. a</note> a new born babe, that hath no manner of ſelf-wiſdom or ſelf-willedneſs, but that liveth only that life that is given and brought unto him by God. In ſuch a manner is the man meet alſo to come into the Kingdom<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ioh. 3 a</note> of God, to enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into.</p>
               <p n="20">20. But behold, with ſuch a heart and mind cometh the man unto the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Deut. 6.10. b. 1 King. 15.</note> true obedience, which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth: And ſo through Faith he goeth out of all deadly corruption or perdition, and cometh into the life of his God, in the everlaſting immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, in all Love: and is filled with all fulneſs of the holy Ghoſt,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 8. b</note> and inherriteth with Chriſt, all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures &amp; riches of God, and of<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 33. a Col. 2. a</note> the ſpiritual and heavenly goods: Thoſe verily are the promiſes of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through Jeſus Chriſt, to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171452:49"/>
of all the generations of the earth.</p>
               <p n="21">21. By this means, as is ſaid, the man cometh again to his ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to his<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ioh. 8. d</note> precious freedom, whereunto<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen. 1. c Sap. 2. c Eccleſ. 17. a</note> God hath created him from the beginning: as being unbound, or untyed from all vain and unprofitable things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:171452:49"/>
               <head>The tenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>NOW when as the ſervice of the offering in the holy hath once had his full courſe, with ſuch a good will as is aforeſaid: and the debt-offering, ſin-offering, and death-offering, is all through the like-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt, accompliſhed on the Altar, through the belief; then<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 25 a Math. 27. 2 Cor. 3. b</note> doth the vail, as opening aſunder, divide it ſelf from before the moſt holy: and ſo there is then diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the moſt holy, the mercy-ſeat, the Ark of witneſs, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bread, with many coſtly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures pertaining to the moſt holy Sanctuary; and all that ſanctified likewiſe that is in the holy, with the<note n="(b)" place="margin">He. 9, 10.</note> ſprinkling of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt the high Prieſt, for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171452:50"/>
forgiveneſs of ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That verily is the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the grace of God, touching the ſins of the people, even as God hath promiſed the ſame to the houſe of Iſrael, and to the houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> for a ſtedfaſt and continuing Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This high Prieſt over the houſe of God, is the old antient one in the holy and godly underſtanding, and is the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Col. 1.</note> firſt born of all creatures,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Rom. 6 a Phil. 2. a</note> who was ſlain with the death of the Croſs, and hath ſuffered in the holy, for the ſins cauſe: and is<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. c Col. 1. b</note> as the firſtling riſen from the death, where-through he hath prepared the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life for all his Believers, which follow after him in the holy<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat 16. c Rom 6. a 1 Pet. 2.</note> till unto the death of his Croſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He himſelf verily is the Light and Life that is everlaſting, which was<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ioh. 1. a Pſal. 210 a</note> with the Father from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and is at the right hand of the<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 1. a</note> Almighty, in the heavenly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or eſtate, who alſo as high Prieſt, entreth into the moſt holy, maketh
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171452:50"/>
alive his believers, from<note n="(k)" place="margin">Rom. 8. b 1 Cor. 15. b Eph. 2. a. b Col. 1.2 b</note> the death and<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eze. 36. c Iſa. 44. a Ioel 2. c Act. 2. b</note> poureth forth the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly over them,<note place="margin">The true, moſt holy of the holy and true Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God, is the Love, the everlaſting life, and the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from which moſt holy in his ſervice (that is in the making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live from the death, in the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the holy Ghoſt, and in miniſtring of the ſpiritual and heavenly good) the vale is put away, whereby to inherit the everlaſting life of God in his cleerneſs, in the ſame ſervice mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred under the obedience of the Love of the holy Ghoſt, which moſt holy in his ſervice, maketh right difference betwixt the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the dead; for in that ſame ſervice doth the reſurrection of the righteous life from the death, come to paſs or is wrought; and that is the joy of life, proceeding out of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly being in the Kingdom of God the Father, with Chriſt in the everlaſting life.</note> to an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bleſſing; and that is the perfection of all that which goeth before, and the moſt holy of the true Tabernacle of God and Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This high Prieſt in the moſt holy, (namely in the Love, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, and the perfection) is a King<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa. 110. Heb. 5. a. b. c 7. c. 8. a</note> and Prieſt for ever, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi> as an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Saviour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:171452:51"/>
to his people to their eternal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God the Father, and he himſelf doth through himſelf, herit them, or make them heirs in the everlaſting life; and that is the eſtabliſhing of the true Teſtament, which continueth firm for ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For through the light of the ſame Teſtament, is Gods Law, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſa. 40. a Iſa. 51. a Ier. 31. d Heb. 8.10.</note> plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the hearts of the Believers: and given unto them in their minds: And God remembreth no more of all their former ſins, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171452:51"/>
that is the eſtabliſhing of the promiſes of God the Father and of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Among thoſe children of the New Teſtament, or holy Goſpel, the vail is<note n="(o)" place="margin">Iſa. 25. a 2 Cor 3. b</note> put away from the moſt holy, and the precious garniſhings of the ſpiritual and heavenly goods, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and brought unto them, as an everlaſting heritage of God and Chriſt: and they (namely) the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the New Teſtament, be taught in that ſort to the Kingdom of God, and made heirs in the everlaſting life,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ro. 12. b Eph 4. a Col. 3. b 1 Pet. 3 a</note> and have nor uſe any thing but Love, Peace and Unity one with other, and a good conſcience in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt through the holy Ghoſt, the Love of God the Father, which God<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rom. 5. a Tit. 3. b</note> hath poured abundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Behold<note n="(r)" place="margin">Apo. 12 a</note> that is the true <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which deſcended from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and alſo the moſt holy of the true Tabernacle of God, which is prepared of God from everlaſting, and which by Gods grace is come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:171452:52"/>
us in this ſame laſt time: In the which <hi>Sion</hi> is eſtabliſhed,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Iſa. 2. a Mich. 4. a</note> out of the which the Law and the word of the Lord proceedeth:<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iſa. 1 c Zach. 8. c</note> And unto the which all people, which have a luſt toward God, ſhall aſſemble them, and rejoyce them therein, according to the Promiſes: For it is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life full of all vertues, and the undiſturbable<note n="(u)" place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> Kingdom full of all Love, peace and godlineſs, wherein that ſong<note n="(w)" place="margin">Apo. 19. a</note> Allelu-jah, is ſung for an everlaſting ſong of laud unto God.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Behold this Kingdom full of all pure beauty, full of light and life, and full of all delightfulneſs and riches of God the Father and of Chriſt, hath been long hidden and unknown for the ſins cauſe of the people, by reaſon of which ſin, the children of men have not beheld this glorious cleerneſs, neither can they endure the beholding of the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful cleerneſs.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Becauſe now of this blindneſs of the darkneſs which hath covered
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:171452:52"/>
the earth &amp; becauſe of the unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the manly generation: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the eter. rich bountiful God been forced to reſerve or keep ſecret, all thoſe things in the holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng:<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eph. 1. b</note> which riches of God the Father, are now notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding coming unto all good will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ones, which love the peace for an everlaſting heritage, according to the Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. With which beauty of the heavenly riches of God, God is now in the laſt time a drawing of us all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to wit all we which are good-willing towards him and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and which for the peaces cauſe do ſubmit our ſelves under the Love, whereby to make known unto us through his Love, and through the declaring of his heavenly riches, his holy will, to an health to the earth, and to the honour and glory of God: and verily now in the laſt times, to a joy and peace, in all love; to the end to prepare in that manner, under the obedience of the Love an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171452:53"/>
peace upon earth, according to the Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Therefore<note n="(y)" place="margin">Deu. 32. a</note> rejoyce you ye heavens and earth, which hope upon God: For behold<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſa. 62.</note> the ſalvation of God is now come that it may be revealed, to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 112. a Eph. 1. b Heb. 1. b</note> renewing of all things that are waxen old: for<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 61 66 2 Pet. 3 b Apo 21. a</note> the new heaven, and the new earth, wherein righteouſneſs dwelleth, and which perpetually continue before God, upon which men have waited according to the Promiſes, do now come with triumph in glory.</p>
               <p n="13">13. In which very ſame time,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa 28. a</note> the Lord will be a lovely crown and glorious garland unto his people that remain over: and a ſpirit of equity unto thoſe that ſet in Judgement, and a ſtrength unto thoſe which come again from the battle to the gates.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Even thus verily in thoſe daies ſhall God perform all good towards Iſrael, and eſtabliſh among them, all what he hath promiſed and covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them in times paſt, by the mouth of his Prophets.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:171452:53"/>15. For the chaſtiſement executed for the ſins cauſe over the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and over the miſerable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſs ones, over<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 54. a</note> whom all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts do happen or come, ſhall ceaſe: and they ſhall revive all beauty, peace and delightfulneſs, and be<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 45 a 1 Ioh. 2 c</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the oyl or ointment of joy; for the Scripture, the Law, and the Prophets ſhall be fulfilled and not broken: and it ſhall come to paſs over the world, and alſo over the Lords people, even as it is written thereof: The Lord grant us mercy and lead us into his wayes, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:171452:54"/>
               <head>The eleventh Chapter.</head>
               <p>HEre have we figured forth unto you, ye dearly beloved, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain circle: In the which we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto you in writing, and figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively ſet forth, both the way of the heathenſhip, or of the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed ones,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 7. b Luk. 13. c</note> which leadeth or reacheth to the everlaſting death and condemnation, (whoſe death, being or eſtate, is the ſtrange being, before or in the ſight of the Lords people Iſrael) As alſo contrary wiſe, the ſimple and plain way,<note n="(b)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 7 a Math. 7.</note> of the good-willing hearts to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which leadeth to the entrance of the true Tabernacle of God in the ſpirit, and reacheth to the everlaſting life.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man standing on globe with snakes protruding from sphere</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Curſing Bleſsing</p>
                  <p>The Inward Man</p>
                  <p>Through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man ſimple, of heart humbled to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſdom vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpright virtue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atient in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlyneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>k minded &amp; faythfull and cometh alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> joy &amp; to God &amp; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> everlaſting</p>
                  <p>The forth go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng in the heatheniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> impurity bringeth the man to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſix of Death</p>
                  <p>The forth go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng in the feare of God &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bringeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man to the Righteouſneſs of the Life</p>
                  <p>The ſin of death bringeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man into all Ignorance hipocriſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> falſehood &amp; into all choſen holyneſs according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and is therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratefull bitter and cruel and alſo, diſpaireth and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtructionable calamity and to the divel hell and Condemnation</p>
               </figure>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:171452:55"/>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 4 a</note>2. If the man now have by Gods grace, gotten a good will to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the upright way, directing to the everlaſting life then muſt he with his heart,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa 51 b 2 Cor 6 b Apo. 18 a</note> depart out of the heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or uncircumciſion, and out of the ſtraying being or nature, yea from all what is not any being of God, alſo ſeparate himſelf from the darkneſs, and turn him<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa 55. a Ier 18.25. a 35. b Ezek 18 d. Ioel 2. b</note> to the Lord his God, namely to the God of life the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ioh 1.</note> true light, full of light and life, who hath created both him and all what is an thing,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk. 1.2. b. c.</note> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fear the ſame living God; and circumciſe his heart from<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deu. 10. b. 30 a</note> all manner of darkneſs, namely from all abominations of deſolation, which do ſeparate the man from the living God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See or annoint your eyes with eye-ſalve, that ye may ſee,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Deu 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b. Ier. 4. a</note> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe your ſelves, or put away the foreskin of your hearts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue not ſtiff-necked, for that ye may rightly underſtand and know the true life, which is a life
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:171452:55"/>
unto you, and may live therein.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For even therefore, becauſe that the life might now in the ſame day, through our<note n="(l)" place="margin">Deu 30. b Eccleſ. 25. a</note> moſt holy ſervlce of the Love, be underſtood from the death, and the light known from the darkneſs; So have we out of the Love to the righteouſneſs, deſcribed and figuratively ſet forth, even in the moſt evident manner, here in the ſame Circle, both theſe wayes, both of death and of the life, and all the ends whereunto each one hath his paſſage or courſe. The which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man entreth into, or liveth there, whether it<note n="(m)" place="margin">Exo. 18. Rom. 6.8. a</note> be then the deadly ſins, extending to the eternal death, or elſe the righteouſneſs to the everlaſting life.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hereunto next adjoyning, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Figurative deſcription or declaration of the inward Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God, according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, after the which we do treat at length in large manner of both theſe natures, which do bring in either the death or the life; and we have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:171452:56"/>
ſignified or marked out by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the names both of the confuſed and of the Godly being or nature. Take it to heart, for it yieldeth to every one of us, either the death or the life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:171452:56"/>
               <head>The twelfth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE true fore-front of the houſe of God, or of the true Tabernacle<note n="(a)" place="margin">Deu. 10. c Eccleſ. 1.26.</note> is the fear of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, ſerving to a turning away from the ſin, and from all heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh fooliſhneſs. Through whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and through the obedience of the requiring thereof, the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh circumciſed in his heart, in<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 12. a 1 Pet. 24. a</note> the laying away of the ſin in the fleſh, and to the obtaining of the knowledge of the truth of God, entreth into the way of peace.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>heart</figDesc>
                  <p>Feare God</p>
                  <p>The Way to the Truth In this ſame ſervice of the holy and gratious word vnder the Obedience of the Love in the feare of God cometh to paſs in the hart and minde the vpright repentance of the man to the living God and ſo walking in the fears of God he is circumcized of hart and is turned away from all the bewiching of the heatheniſh being that he may not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched or taken with any destruction but be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the entrance into the Sanctuary of God. Jer: 4. Eezek: 4.4: wherefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you with all your hart in the ſpirit and feare the Everlasting invisible God which is the bgin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to come to the Wiſdome or the firſt entrance of the true Tabernacle or houſe of God in the ſpirit. Whereof God himſelfe is the Workman Turne ye not therefore from the lord in your hart nether truſt in men nor take fleſh for your Arme or Strength and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Curſing</p>
               </figure>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:171452:57"/>2. For the ſame circumciſion of the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Phi. 3. a Col. 2 b</note> heart, is the true circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which cometh to paſs in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of man, but of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ier. 4 a</note> circumciſe the foreskin of your hearts, and be not hence forth ſtiffnecked any longer, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Plough<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eze. 10. b</note> upon the new, and ſow not among the thorns; circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe you unto the Lord, and put away the foreskin of your hearts ye men of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ye people at <hi>Jeruſalem, Jer.</hi> 4. a.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There ſhall none<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſa. 52. Ioel. 3.</note> come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lords ſanctuary that hath an uncircumciſed heart, and an uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed fleſh <hi>Eze.</hi> 44. b.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Therefore ſhall the Lord thy God circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy ſeed,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Deu. 10. c Math. 22.</note> that thou maiſt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, that thou mayeſt live. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If thou<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deu. 10 c Iſa. 19 b</note> wilt turn thee O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:171452:58"/>
then turn uno me, ſaith the Lord; and if thou wilt put away<note n="(i)" place="margin">Jer. 15. b Zach 1. a Mal. 3. a</note> thine abominations from before my face, then ſhalt thou not be driven out, but then ſhalt thou without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, ſwear rightly and holily, (as true as the Lord liveth) and the heathen ſhall be bleſſed in him, and make their boaſt of him, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4. a.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 4 b Luk. 4. a</note> him ſhalt thou ſerve, him ſhalt thou cleave unto or depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſwear by his name, he is thy praiſe and thy God: <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. a. 10. b</p>
               <p n="9">9. Behold the Heaven, and the Heaven of all Heavens, and the earth, and all what is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal 24. a Ier. 27 a</note> is the Lords your God, O <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Deut. 4. d</note> yet hath he had notwithſtanding a luſt only to your Fathers, and loved them, and choſen their ſeed after them, namely you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10 b.</p>
               <p n="10">10. O all ye people, fear the ſame God, for he is that God which hath created<note n="(n)" place="margin">Gen. 1. a Ioh. 1. a</note> all whatſoever is any thing; for truly all heatheniſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:171452:58"/>
is nothing but fooliſhneſs: Their wiſdom and Laws are meer er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Iſa. 44. a Ier. 10. a</note> their Gods and God-ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are vain and unprofitable.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Therefore there is no God but Iſraels God, whoſe God-ſervices, Wiſdom, Ordinances, Statutes and Rights are alone upright, holy, and true, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. a.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Happy is he that hath the ſame God to be<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſa. 33. b 144. b</note> his God, or which ſeeketh him with all his heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. c. 30. a. <hi>Ier.</hi> 29. b. Sap. 1. a.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:171452:59"/>
               <head>The thirteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE true holy of the houſe of God or of the true Tabernacle is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 5. a</note> the belief of Chriſt unto Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: through whoſe ſervice, and the obedience unto the requiring thereof, the man if he have a luſt with all his heart,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſa. 40. a Heb. 10. a</note> to do the Lords will, becometh Juſtified from the ſin. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the way of his courſe of walking, prepared<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 40 a 57. b.</note> to be an even path be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord. And the truth of God extending to the everlaſting life revealed unto him in the ſpirit.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>heart</figDesc>
                  <p>Beleefe</p>
                  <p>The Truth to the Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rlasting Life In the ſervice of the holy and gratious word Vnder the Obedience of the true beleefe is the man in the ſpirit of his hart in Jeſus Christ juſtified from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sin and brought to the everlasting life Therefore beare patience and vpright fruites of repentance The Kingdom of heaven is nigh Mat: 3 a Luke 3 a Behold ſo crieth the Voice in the Wilderneſs of the Mans harte The which crieth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way of the lord make ſtraite his pathes Esay. 40. Behold the word that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt beleeue is nigh thee even in thy mouth and in thine hart that thou mighteſt doe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deutri: 30 and that is the word of beleefe which formerly hath beene preached in the World through Chriſt to Salvation and Obedience of the Beleefe Rom. 10. And is now preached under the Obedience of the Love</p>
               </figure>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:171452:60"/>2. Behold the Lord ſendeth forth his<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mal. 3. a Math. 11. b</note> Angel or Meſſenger, who in his ſervice prepareth the way<note n="(e)" place="margin">Math. 4 a Luk 1. b</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and he goeth before, in the ſpirit or power of <hi>Elias,</hi> that he may turn the hearts of the Fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their Fathers, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers to the prudence of the juſt, whereby to prepare an upright peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How delightful are the feet of the<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o 10 b</note> meſſengers that publiſh the peace from the mountains, preach a good Meſſage, and reveal the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. <hi>Nahum</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Leave off from the evil, and learn to do good: labour after that which is right and help the oppreſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. b.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let the ungodly leave off from his waies<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eze. 18 33. b.</note> and the evil doer from his imaginations, and turn him to the Lord, ſo ſhall he be merciful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. a.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Let every one turn him away from his wicked wayes, and amend
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:171452:60"/>
his being or life, and ſo do that which is right, <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. a.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If the ungodly will turn him from all the ſins that he hath done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then ſhall he live and not dye; for the Lord deſireth not the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Eze. 33. b Sap. 1. b</note> death of a ſinner, but much rather that he ſhould turn him and live, <hi>Eze.</hi> 18. d.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Repent now and amend you, that your ſins may be put out, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. b.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Lay away from you now,<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. b 4. a.</note> according to the former walking the old man, which deſtroyeth through the luſt of error,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ro. 12. a</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new you in the ſpirit of your mind, and put ye on the new man which is formed like unto God, in upright righteouſneſs and holyneſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. c.</p>
               <p n="10">10. But before all things, take hold of the Shield of Faith, with the which we may quench out all the fiery darts of the wicked enemy, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. b.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Hold faſt what thou haſt, that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:171452:61"/>
no man bereave or take away thy Crown from thee, <hi>Apo.</hi> 3. b.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whoſoever continueth ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt unto the end, he ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. b.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The Meſſenger or voice of the Angel, which crieth in the heart, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare<note n="(l)" place="margin">ſa. 40. a</note> the way of the Lord, is the ſerviceable miniſtration of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious word of the Lord, which the Lord willeth to be miniſtred unto the man before<note n="(m)" place="margin">Act. 3.17. c.</note> his revealing of his great day. By which means in the grace and mercy of the Lord.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> the belief, that very true holy, and the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Heb. 10 b</note> boldneſs to enter into the ſame, is prepared to ſerve the man to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of the ſervice in the ſaid holy: whereby the true fore-going ſervice might likewiſe be miniſtred unto the Believers in their converſion unto God, and in their doing<note n="(p)" place="margin">Math. 3.</note> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right fruits of repentance. Alſo to kill<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rom 6. a Col. 2. b</note> and bury the ſame, under the obedience of the belief. And through the baptiſing or waſhing<note n="(r)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a Col. 1 b</note> in the death of Chriſt, to juſtifie the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:171452:61"/>
believing man from the ſin.</p>
               <p n="14">14. And ſo then after that, in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling or accompliſhing the ſame fore-going ſervice, cometh the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mat. 19. c Ioh. 3. b</note> new birth from the death, through the annointing by our Saviour, who doth quite and clean take away or blot out the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Heb 9.</note> ſins of his people: and ſo in his ſpiritual office or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly miniſtration, ſerveth them<note n="(u)" place="margin">Heb. 8.</note> with the ſpiritual and heavenly goods, and leadeth them into the everlaſting life, and ſo bringeth the perfection unto them, or ſetteth up the ſame in them, and as<note n="(x)" place="margin">Heb. 7, 8, 9.</note> a chief Prieſt, declareth his<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 27. a Math. 27.</note> higheſt ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto them, in the moſt holy, (namely in the Love, which is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Ghoſt) where through the vail be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the holy and the moſt holy, and<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſa. 59. a Eph. 2. b Col. 2. a</note> the portion betwixt God and the man departeth away, and of two<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 2. b.</note> is made one, to wit the man and God.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That verily is the everlaſting<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 3. a 2 Cor. 5. c Col. 1. b Ioh. 2. a 4. b</note> reconcilement of the man before his God: and ſo he cometh again to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:171452:62"/>
the ſeat of grace, and into the true light of the<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. b. 4. a</note> clear ſhining of God, and into the everlaſting life, with thankſgiving and jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; the which is the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 60. a Apo. 21. a</note> true riſing of the light and life out of the high heaven in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:171452:62"/>
               <head>The fourteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE true vale before the moſt holy of the true Sanctuary of the Tabernacle of God,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb 10. c</note> is the fleſh of Chriſt, the which is before the cleerneſs of his uncovered naked being or ſubſtance, and before his ſpiritual and heavenly goods, and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 27. 2 Cor 3. b</note> it departeth away therefrom, or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it ſelf aſunder, when the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going ſervice in the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb 9 c</note> holy is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the vail before the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleerneſs of the Godly being of Jeſus Chriſt, and before his ſpiritual and heavenly goods, departeth not away from before the cleerneſs of the moſt holy<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 7, 8, 9.10.</note> unleſs that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer God ſervice in the holy, have firſt his full courſe: the which is the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:171452:63"/>
accompliſhment of the daily God-ſervice in the holy; in the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 16. Luk. 9. c</note> taking up of our Croſs, in the willing obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the belief, for to continue therein obediently, till<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> unto the end, that is till unto the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a Phil. 2. b.</note> death of the Croſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which death of the Croſs of Chriſt, and to be implanted or incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into Chriſt, with the ſame like death, and ſo<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a Col. 2. b.</note> baptiſed or waſhed into his death, is verily the<note n="(i)" place="margin">Math. 28. Mar. 16 b</note> upright Baptiſm unto ſalvation, wherein the man is rightly baptiſed or waſhed, according to the truth of the holy Scriptures; and ſo then<note n="(k)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a</note> out of the ſame death regenerate<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. b</note> or born again, as a new Creature in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For that the ſame<note n="(m)" place="margin">Tit. 3 b 1 Pet. 3. c</note> baptiſm is the right font of regeneration, ſerving to the waſhing away of the ſin, wherethrough the believing man, who doth with Chriſt according to the fleſh, lay away, mortifie and<note n="(n)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a Col. 2. c. 3. a</note> bury the ſin in the fleſh, is made alive
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:171452:63"/>
again with Chriſt; and alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſpirit, in upright<note n="(o)" place="margin">Luk 14. Eph. 1. a. 4. b</note> righteouſneſs and holyneſs, and ſo through the ſecond birth, from the death, or the reſurrection of Chriſt, he becometh holy and altogether renewed in the ſpirit of his inward mind, and the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Act. 2. b.</note> holy Ghoſt poured upon him, in whom Chriſt alſo with the cleerneſs of his Godly being getteth<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. a Gal. 4. a</note> a ſhape or form.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>banner in front of stage</figDesc>
                  <head>By the high priest Ieſus Christ the new and liuing way is prepared for us through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay his fleſh Heb 10</head>
               </figure>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:171452:64"/>5. And that ſame verily, is<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Co. 13. b. 2 Cor. 3. b</note> the cleerneſs of the true being, and of the holy ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, where through one beholdeth and inherit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the ſpirit the Love in her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous nature, that moſt holy, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the fulneſs of the riches of God the Father, in the heavenly being or eſſential form.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Behold and conſider, that is the true<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ioh. 11. c</note> reſurrection from the death according to the Scripture,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Ioh. 17. a</note> through the which the living God of heaven and his Chriſt is known accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Spirit and Truth.</p>
               <p n="7">7, It is true, the<note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. c.</note> ſame is ſown in the mortality, and it riſeth up in the immortality: And God giveth it a body after his own pleaſure, and that of the ſeed of his own body.</p>
               <p n="8">8. See that is the everlaſting life, againſt the death. And the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eze. 13. b 1 Cor. 15. f Heb. 2. b</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt or victory againſt the Hell, and againſt all the enemies of the life, whereby all thoſe that follow after Chriſt, have or poſſeſs that life, and<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ioh. 10. b</note> that in fulneſs.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:171452:65"/>9. That is verily the<note n="(z)" place="margin">Heb. 3.4. a.</note> Reſt of life, which God hath reſerved or kept, and is left in ſtore for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, as a perpetual inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the laſt time, according to the Promiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:171452:65"/>
               <head>The fifteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE true moſt holy of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Tabernacle or Sanctuary of God, is the Love; for that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 13. Col. 3. b</note> is the perfection,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 6. a</note> the incorporating into God in the ſpirit, the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Col. 2. b</note> and the fulneſs of all the riches of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If one now be not<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ioh. 1. a</note> born anew, then can he not ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore if there be a new<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. a Gal. 6. c</note> creature in Chriſt, then is the old<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 43. c Apo. 21.</note> periſhed or worn out; behold it is all become new, but that altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, who<note n="(h)" place="margin">Col. 1. b</note> hath reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us with himſelf through Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord our Almighty God
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:171452:66"/>
hath gotten<note n="(i)" place="margin">Apo 12.</note> the Kingdom; let us rejoyce and be glad, and give<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> him the honour: for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his bride hath made her ready, and it is granted unto her to cloath her ſelf with white gliſtering ſilk, and the ſilk is the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the Saints, <hi>Apo.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Members or Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body of Chriſt in the love, which are<note n="(l)" place="margin">Act. 2. Rom 8. b Eph. 1.4. c</note> ſealed with Chriſt, in the true being, through the ſpirit of Love, is<note n="(m)" place="margin">Apo. 21.</note> a living Tabernacle of God, wherein God liveth and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: In the which the fore-front, the holy and the moſt holy, is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or made known according to the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In which true Tabernacle of God alſo the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of God, and the ſong of the Lamb is ſung, and it ſoundeth even thus.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>heart</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>EM<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ANVEL</hi>
                  </p>
                  <head>God and Man</head>
                  <p>Loue</p>
                  <p>The everlasting life &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfection in the ſervice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy, gratious word vnder the obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Love God with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man is vnited, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God head (namely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> everlasting mind &amp; being &amp; all with God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> christ it is of one being with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man, &amp; all what is manly be it the being will &amp; mind &amp; is then minded w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God head, &amp; ſo it is all one God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man one being one will, one thought or ſpirit, one hart &amp; one everlasting life. Behold here the tabernacle of God is in men, &amp; hee ſhall live in them &amp; they ſhalbe his people &amp; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e himſelfe ſhalbe with them for he is their God Apoca: 21: the Kingdom of God ſhall not cvm with outward ſhew, men ſhall not ſay Behold here or there it is for behold the Kingdom of God is inwardly in you Luke: 17: this ſaith the Truth of God, who loveth mee he ſhall keepe my words and my father ſhall love him and wee ſhall come to him and make an habitation in him John: 14:</p>
               </figure>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:171452:67"/>7. Great and wonderful are thy Works Lord,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ier. 10. a</note> thou Almighty God; righteous and true are thy wayes thou King of Saints; Lord, who ſhould not fear thee, and praiſe thy name? for thou only<note n="(p)" place="margin">Levit. 19.</note> art holy, <hi>Apo.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Conſider now, how that the mans knowledge is but<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Cor. 13</note> a peice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, or a thing unperfect, the which among thoſe that do yet remain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided or as broken off is alſo divided, or as a thing broken off from the incorporating to the Love, the very perfect being or ſubſtance: In like manner is alſo the prophecying: yet are they both, namely the knowledge and the prophecying, ſerviceable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the man in the fore-going ſervice, before the true being; and do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto him,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 13. b Luk. 8. a</note> as in a ſecret word, the cleerneſs of the Love or of the true being</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:171452:67"/>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:171452:68"/>9. Unto which true being, the knowledge and the prophecying do point in the ſervice of the holy word; as that the ſame is coming to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in uncovered cleerneſs of God, whereby they<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Cor. 10 3. b.</note> may behold the ſame, from face to face, and to continue heirs therein with all the Saints of God for evermore.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And that is the Love, the true being and the perfection of all the riches of God, where Chriſt the ſpiritual and heavenly high Prieſt, is a Miniſter unto us, in<note n="(t)" place="margin">Heb 8, 9, b</note> thoſe ſame ſpiritual and heavenly goods. For<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ro. 11. b</note> of him, through him, and in him, are all things, to whom be praiſe for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Now at the end of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the former Tabernacle, when as the ſame perfection<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Cor. 13. b</note> cometh unto us or appeareth<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 60. 2 Pet. 1 c</note> as a day-light from on high: then doth alſo the peice-work or that which is in part as likewiſe the childiſh under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding touching the Godly things ceaſe, or leave off with us; for the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:171452:68"/>
being of the man,<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. b Eph. 4. b</note> or the old age in the manly underſtanding of the new birth in Jeſus Chriſt, layeth off or putteth away the childiſh compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending; it is very true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:171452:69"/>
               <head>The ſixteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>TO the end now that all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings might be ſatisfied, and that the Books of the myſtery, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the diſcerning into the being of God, or the holy of his Saints, and the diſcerning into the Devils being, or the abomination of deſolation of his wicked members) might<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo. 5. a</note> not ſtill continue ſhut: Therefore will we, out of an inclination to the Love, diſcover, ſhew, or witneſs out of that ſight which we have in the truth, ſo much as we can, and perceive to be profitable, the beings and properties of them both, whereby we may alſo reveal the ſecret treaſure of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Apo. 9 12, 13, 16, 17.</note> and the Dragon, or the Beaſt of the bottomleſs Pit, that falſe Prophet which hath ſeduced the whole world, and made her drunken with his unchaſtity, ſo to diſcloſe or
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:171452:69"/>
diſplay in evident manner before the eyes of all people, that falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly nature. And nakedly or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently to ſhew, wherein he hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered or hid himſelf hitherto in the world, with deceit and falſhood; And with what manner of form or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of his wicked members, he hath dwelt in the hearts and minds of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wherethrough the man hath in ſo divers manners committed whoredom and Adultery<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ier. 2. d 3. a. Eze. 16. c Eze. 4.5. a</note> againſt his God, and ſo through the bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his mind, wit, and thoughts, hath ſerved the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ap. 9.13, 14, 16, 17.</note> beaſt of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit, honoured the Devil, and worſhipped the Dragon, even in that place, where he ſhould<note n="(e)" place="margin">Deut. 4.6. b Mat. 4 b.</note> ſerve and honour his God only; by reaſon whereof, it is grown everywhere full of abominations of deſolation: the which<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 24. b 2 Theſ. 20.</note> hath gotten and poſſeſſeth the holy place, like as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. 9. c</note> hath ſpoken thereof, with which horrible faſhion or monſtrous diſpoſition of the enemies of God,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:171452:70"/>
the whole world is governed,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Apo. 14. a 18. a. b</note> and therein are all heathen drowned or overwhelmed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Even thus hath the wicked cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, who laboureth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it all, a long time held forth his own book, or his own wiſdom, as a book of life or conſolation before the man, for a delight or pleaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and hath taken him captive, or bound him under the ſame, which book are the bands of the Devil, and the<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. a Apo. 20 a</note> chains of darkneſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Therefore is the Lamb killed<note n="(k)" place="margin">Apo. 5.13. a. b</note> from the beginning, and thruſt out of his Kingdom, and the ſtrangers have poſſeſſed his<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſa 78 a</note> heritage with unrighteouſneſs: laid his Kingdom waſt with their abominations: trodden down the living book of the Lamb with feet: not willing or allowing that the man ſhould look into, read or live the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. See in that manner is the mans upright underſtanding, of the truth ſtolen away from him, and he is turned into a corrupt or
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:171452:70"/>
falſe underſtanding and into a lying being or eſtate: and the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers who through their falſhod have poſſeſſed the heritage of the Lamb, have alſo comforted the man, with a vain and falſe comfort: becauſe that the book of the Lamb might alwayes continue ſhut, and the ſeals thereof never to be opened;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Apo 5 a</note> for when as his ſeals be once opened,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Apo. 6. b 20. b</note> then cometh forth the Judgement accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the truth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Now when the ſeals of the book of the Lamb be opened, and that the ſame book is read, then become the names of the Saints manifeſt, which are written in the Book of the Lamb: and through the Lamb, and the Saints illumination or brightneſs, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh likewiſe ſeen and known the great and manifold deceit of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemy, that Adverſary unto God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Through which light of the Lamb, the enemy of God muſt loſe and leave the ſeat of his poſſeſſion: even thus is then his peace taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the earth; and he himſelf
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:171452:71"/>
as a deſtroyer rejected on the earth, for to be deſtroyed, which hath ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times corrupted and deſtroyed the earth.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Therethrough now cometh the killing upon earth, and the murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among all ungodly ones, in ſuch ſort that through their impugning or reſiſtance againſt the Lamb, their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment cometh over themſelves, and they fall to be many dead bodies upon the earth.</p>
               <p n="9">9. See in ſuch manner do then the Kingdoms<note n="(o)" place="margin">Apo. 12 a</note> of the world become the Lords, and his Chriſts, who ſhall raign for ever and ever: before whom all Elders or wiſdoms do fall down, and worſhip him which liveth for ever and ever: witneſſing and ſaying unto him,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Apo 4. b</note> Lord, thou art worthy to receive praiſe, honour and power; for thou haſt created every thing; and for thine own ſake, they have their being, and were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p n="10">10. For ſeeing now, that Gods Judgement is<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 8. b</note> acccording to the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:171452:71"/>
truth, and not according to the judgement of men, therefore do we find very truly, according to the truth, That Gods ſecret mind and judgement is far different from the mind and judgement of men.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Therefore it is in no wiſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any man to know,<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. b</note> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the truth, except that he ſhould firſt of all be or ſtand groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein according to the ſpirit: and that the truth as a light of life, repugning or ſtriving againſt his lyes, were riſen up unto him in his obeying of the requiring of the ſervice of Love: For in that ſort do we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to know the truth from the lye, the life from the death, and the ſin from the righteouſneſs: Becauſe that we ſhould rightly or according to the truth, hate or reject that which is worthy to be hated or rejected; and according to the truth in like manner love that which is worthy to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: And ſo then might with a good underſtanding, come to<note n="(s)" place="margin">Eph. 4 b</note> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:171452:72"/>
of the right commonalty of Saints, whoſe names are written in the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Apo. 5.20, 21. b</note> living Book of the Lamb.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Which Book of the Lamb, the myſticalneſs of God ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remain ſhut, but his ſeals ſhall be opened, and the book being full of writing both without and within, ſhall likewiſe be read to a comfort of life, and to a perpetual Godlyneſs, unto all thoſe whoſe names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of the Lamb, whoſe bodies are killed even like unto the Lamb: and<note n="(u)" place="margin">Apo. 6. b</note> their blood cryeth vengeance in the height, upon thoſe that dwell upon the earth, unto whom the recompence thereof ſhall be made by God and the Lamb.</p>
               <p n="13">13. For although the Lamb be killed, yet ſhall he notwithſtanding condemn the living ungodly ones, and raiſe up thoſe that are his<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eze 37. b Dan. 12 b Ioh 5. c 1 Cor. 15. f</note> from the death out of the grave, and make them Lordly and glorious with himſelf over all his enemies, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through his righteous judgement,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:171452:72"/>
to the<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 25. c 2 Pet. 3 b</note> condemnation of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ones, to the end that they may be rooted out, and<note n="(z)" place="margin">Apo. 18 a</note> that it may be recompenced again even as they have done unto the Saints of God.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Even thus now from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be reputed for a praiſe or an advancement, unto all that are his, whereby to keep the judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every one which hath brought forth ungodlyneſs, judged Gods truth falſly, and ſhewed no repentance; and to exhalt and garniſh his Saints above all what is upon the earth: for<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo 5 b 1 Pet 1. b</note> the Lamb hath bought them with his blood, out of all generations, people, and nations: He hath made them Kings and Prieſts unto God, and they ſhall raign upon the earth, and triumph in joy everlaſtingly with the Lamb; for they ſhall live for ever, and not dye any more.</p>
               <p n="15">15. And that ſame is the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, which was preached in the world in times paſt, to the end that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:171452:73"/>
men ſhould believe on the ſame; And which alſo cometh unto us in the laſt time, in the reſurrection of the righteous dead ones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:171452:73"/>
               <head>The ſeventeenth Chap.</head>
               <p>THerefore give ear, O all ye that live upon the earth, conſider of the words of wiſdom, ye children of men. For the life, to the end that ye may live, is now publiſhed unto you likewiſe as well as unto the people<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 6.18, 19. Exo. 3, 4. Deut. 3.</note> in times paſt, becauſe that ye may ſhew repentance, aſſemble you with us, to the mercy ſeat of the love of Jeſus Chriſt, and enter<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 3.4. a.</note> into the reſt which is reſerved for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, inaſmuch as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the reſt of the Lord, and of his children or Saints of Jeſus Chriſt, cometh to paſs and is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed now in the laſt time according to the Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore give ear attentively,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:171452:74"/>
that ye may once underſtand where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye are created; and turn you to the ſame, if ye will remain pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and not bide loſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Apply your hearts unto the good, that ye may live, and not be buried in hell everlaſtlngly<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſa 55. Apo. 21, 22.</note> with the ungodly.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Shew upright fruits of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that ye may ſerve the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Deut. 6. b</note> Lord your God only, and walk in all love like children of peace. And halt no longer, neither<note n="(e)" place="margin">3 Kin. 18.</note> on the one ſide nor on the other.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For although that ye which covet after knowledge, do daily read many Scriptures or writings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ye do alſo gather ſome ſentences, or get a certain kind of knowledge therethrough, wherein ye think to rejoyce your ſelves: Yet is not the ſame the life for all that; for it is neither the Scripture, nor yet the knowledge thereof,<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.</note> that maketh us righteous, but the life of Jeſus Chriſt, wrought through the belief or faith.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:171452:74"/>6. For that ſame life is<note n="(g)" place="margin">Deut. 30. Rom. 10.</note> the word of God the Father, and the very true light, wherein we ſtand grounded, or whereon we are ſet for to believe the ſame, becauſe that we ſhould live, and not<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deut. 5. Prov. 4 c</note> turn or ſhrink therefrom with our mind, wits, memory or thoughts, neither to the right ſide nor to the left.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If ſo be now that ye ſtand not minded hereunto, as in tending to live in the Love, and to ſtand upright therein: to what end then do ye aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble together; and to what end do ye read the Scriptures? For if ye read the Scripture only for the knowledge ſake, and reſt unbelieving unto the life whereof the<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.</note> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture witneſſeth, then do ye<note n="(k)" place="margin">3 Kl. 18.</note> halt on both ſides, and break the bond of wedlock, and go a whoring with that which is not the life, namely that ye cleave unto that which ye neither are grounded in, nor created unto by God, neither yet called through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, nor alſo through his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:171452:75"/>
of Love, miniſtred now in the laſt time.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But if ye will perform the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures counſel, then follow the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures counſel, Turn you to the life and to his ſervice of Love; And in the obedience of the requiring of the life of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his ſervice of Love, behold in the ſpirit your own being or eſtate; And conſider there inwardly in your ſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that your memory, wits, ſenſes, and thoughts, do in all their courſe or proceedings, ſtand minded to the true life of Jeſus Chriſt, and not run out after this or after that, for to go a whoring after that which is not the life it ſelf; and alſo whether that they being without the life, are bound or tyed unto any other thing that is not the life: And likewiſe whether they have or gather all their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wiſdom and underſtanding only out of the l fe of Jeſus Chriſt, and out of his love, and ſo do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know, diſcern or underſtand any
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:171452:75"/>
thing without the Life, and without his upright Love. For behold to ſuch a concord hath God joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thoughts and the life.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This doubtleſs was the life of the man in<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gen. 1. b Joh. 1. a</note> the beginning, for that the man ſhould live in peace and joy, and in all upright Love; and ſhould not know nor take on any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſame, but live only therein and not dye.</p>
               <p n="10">10. If ſo be now that the man knew nothing without the ſame fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned life, nor took on any thing beſides the ſame whereon to tye his heart, wits, and thoughts or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: Then ſhould he know, taſte, and feel nothing elſe but all good. Alſo walk in all Love, Concord and Peace, and ſo have<note n="(m)" place="margin">Gen. 1.2. b</note> the whole earth in ſubjection under him: and govern uprightly to the life, all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is upon the earth, according to the commandment or word of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For that ſame is the life, and the freedom of the manly generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:171452:76"/>
for the which many creatures do ſigh and long there-after; which upright freedom of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, doth now come unto us, according to the Promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all manly creatures might aſſemble them with us to the ſame: rejoyce them with Godly joy in the ſame, and live in all truth and upright righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Behold the ſame was unto the man in the beginning<note n="(o)" place="margin">Gen 2. a Phil. 3. b 4 Eſd. 8. f Apoc. 2. a</note> a Tree of life, in the middſt of the Paradiſe of the Lord, for that he ſhould live, and that<note n="(p)" place="margin">Sapl. 1. b</note> it ſhould go well with all that which God had created.</p>
               <p n="13">13. But now when the man would know the good and the evil, and had eaten of the ſame tree, then<note n="(q)" place="margin">Gen. 3 a</note> taſted he both the life and the death, the which God had forbidden him, becauſe he ſhould not eat, nor taſt of any other thing, but of the good (that is of the life) and not feel any evil or death: but ſhould live unto his God in the life, for that<note n="(r)" place="margin">Sap. 1. b</note> it might go well both with himſelf, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:171452:76"/>
alſo with all what God had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whatſoever now therefore is taken on beſides the ſame good or life whereon we do witneſs, that is the evil, the death, or the deſtruction, the which God hath not willed that it ſhould be upon the earth, for that the man might ſtand perfected from all evil and deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="15">15. But now hath the man through that ſame, prepared to himſelf the driving forth out of the Paradiſe of God, and cauſed the peace to ceaſe upon the earth: alſo brought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all what is upon the earth, into<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gen. 3. b</note> much calamity and miſery; and is utterly eſtranged from the way directing to the Tree of life, and ſo is taken captive in all kind of deadly and damnable fruits.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That verily is the knowledge of the good and evil, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath taken on: and<note n="(t)" place="margin">Dan. 9. Math. 24. 2 Theſ 2.</note> it is the confuſed abomination which ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the holy place, whereout all
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:171452:77"/>
violence, calamity and grief is come upon the earth.</p>
               <p n="17">17. If the man now will<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ezek 14. a</note> turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf away from all the abominations of the wicked world, and humble him rightly under the Love and her ſervice, then ſhall he likewiſe through the adminiſtration of the holy word of the Lord, and his requiring, have his regard unto the inward upright life, whereon the word pointeth, (for that is Gods living being or ſubſtance it ſelf) and he ſhall alſo according to the requiring of the word, try or examine himſelf diligently in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, whether he can perceive, yet ſtill remaining there, any ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or deadly being, which is not the life, or that ſerveth not the life unto the life, but which<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eph. 4. b</note> is minded to deſtruction through the luſts of error.</p>
               <p n="18">18. So long then as the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beſides th preſervation of the life, is looked neto, or eſteemed of by the man: and that likewiſe the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:171452:77"/>
death beſides the life, the evil beſides the good, and the bondage beſides the freedom, is known, taſted and felt: ſo ſhall the man in his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the requiring of the word of the Lord, daily<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 10. d 16. c Mark. 8. Luk 9 14.</note> take up his Croſs on him, with the life die the death or the evil, and bury the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of the Lord, and ſo ſhall he by means of following the life in his like behaviour or<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ro. 6. a Phil 3. b</note> death of the Croſs, become planted into the ſame good life, who ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the death of the Croſs by the evil.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Out of which dying of the death, or of the evil (which death hath brought the death unto the life, and hath had the dominion over the ſame) the life riſeth up again, and cometh gloriouſly in Lordly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, againſt all his enemies.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Even thus now, through the riſing up, or reſurrection of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life, out of the ſecond birth from the death the man alſo is raiſed up<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 6. a</note> from the death, (or born
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:171452:78"/>
again out of the death) for that he might live, and not dye any more.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Upon which reſurrection of the dead, according to the Scripture, all Believers of the life do likewiſe hope and long thereafter; for the life ſhall ſwallow up<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eze. 13. 1 Cor. 15.</note> the death in victory, in all his Believers, which be incorporated or planted into him, and ſo bring his enemy under him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="22">22. For all what is not the true life, that is againſt the true life: and whatſoever is againſt the true life, that is the death and the enmity unto the true life, is alſo an enimy unto God, and to the Lamb; which enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is minded neither according to the true being or nature of God, nor of the Lamb, nor yet according to the upright righteouſneſs of the true life; which true being of God and of the Lamb, together with the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right righteouſneſs of the true life, ye may behold in the endleſs<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apo. 5.20. b</note> book of the Lamb, which is full of writing,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:171452:78"/>
both without and within written with the finger of God: and it is the everlaſting life, whereon we do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:171452:79"/>
               <head>The eighteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THen when as thou, O thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man, haſt looked into both theſe Natures, Books and writings inwardly according to the ſpirit, namely the ſtraying being of the wicked world, and the good being of God from eternity: which good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo. 20, 21. b</note> book of the Lamb, written by the God of life: beſides the which, the ſtraying being which deſtroyeth through the luſts of error is come in place, and written by the Devil (the Father of death) So judge then with the truth, which of them it is, that ought to have the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority or preheminence in us: for the od of life vouchſafeth unto us nothing elſe but all God, life, love, and peace.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:171452:79"/>2. Therefore let us be agreeably minded with the ſame good being of God, and Love the good being: for wherefore do ye receive and take un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the deſtruction? and why will ye in perditional manner periſh in miſery and in unreſtfulneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O ye children of men, turn you to the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Deu. 30. c</note> life with humble hearts, and in like manner to the Love that ye may live.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Awake up I pray thee, O thou precious man; for behold death and life,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Deut 3. b Eccleſ. 15. c Ier. 21. a</note> evil and good, deſtruction and preſervation, damnation and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; the old wicked world in the which all wickedneſs dwelleth: and the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa. 61. b 1 Pet. 3. b Apo. 21. a</note> new good world in the which all love, peace and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dwelleth, is held forth or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto thee, and figured out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eyes: therefore chooſe or incline thou now unto that which thou ſeeſt or knowſt to be Gods righteouſneſs, extending to the laud and praiſe of his glory; and apply thy ſelf to live only the ſame, that<note n="(f)" place="margin">Deut. 6. a o. b Math. 4.</note> thou mayeſt ſerve and live unto the Lord thy God only.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:171452:80"/>4. If ſo be now therefore that any one do look into or eſteem the being of the Devil, the treaſury of iniquity,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Sap. 2 4.14. b Rom. 1. c 2. a.</note> and the form or faſhion of the wicked world, to be an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life, tending to the praiſe and glory of God: and if it be the ſame whereunto God hath created the man, to have that raign over him, then let him incline and ſtick unto it, and ſerve the ſame only: and let him ſeparate himſelf from all what is contrary thereunto, and accompany him with thoſe that are of one mind with the iniquity, or with the wicked world, that he may beare or receive either his ſalvation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, with thoſe that are his own members, which are agreeably-minded with each other, and let him<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 King. 18. c</note> halt no longer on both ſides, nor feign nor diſſemble before the upright Love which is held forth and proffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But if now any man do look into or eſteem the Being of God, or Treaſure of vertue, to be the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:171452:80"/>
of men, tending to the land and praiſe of the godly glory, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth or perceiveth that<note n="(i)" place="margin">Gen. 2. c Sap. 2. c Eccleſ. 17. a</note> God hath created the man to that end that the ſame ſhould raign over him: So let him then likewiſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf obediently under the Love, and incline or cleave wholly to the ſame good being, even with a fervent good will, that he may ſerve the ſame only,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Deut. 6. a 10. b. 30. a</note> and live only unto the eternal God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For to that purpoſe is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the word, both by writing and by ſpeech, under the obedience of the Love adminiſtred unto men, to aſſiſt them to the life of God, and to the eternal truth, becauſe they ſhould live in the ſame truth and life, as in a Treaſure of vertue: and that altogether in a lively meek minded being or nature; but not to the end to catch, to ſnare, nor to bring any one into bondage therewith, or to<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Cor. 1. c 1 Pet. 1. a</note> raign over his faith; O no, but in him free or at liberty, to yield to the obedience of the Love, and to the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:171452:81"/>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Luk. 1. g Eph. 1. a</note> righteouſneſs of Faith, becauſe the righteouſneſs of Faith which God eſteemeth of, might by that means be ſet up in the belief under the obedience of the Love. And that the peace might appear upon the earth according to the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For that cauſe, to the end that the life of the eternal truth might be manifeſt, and that the mans under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding might be planted into the ſame life, therefore do we through our ſervice of the holy word, as by an inclination of the Love, take<note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Cor. 10. a</note> captive all underſtandings under the obedience of the Love.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To that end (namely for the Love and the good lifes ſake) ſhall men alſo hear and believe the ſervice of the holy and gracious word, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred under the Love. But with their ſpirits they<note n="(o)" place="margin">Iſa 53. 2 Cor. 6. b</note> ſhall depart out of the evil, or that which is perdition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and enter into the vertue of the life.</p>
               <p n="9">9. For the outward writings or
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:171452:81"/>
ſpeakable words, which be teſtified or miniſtred unto the man, out of the inclination of the Love to do him ſervice and ſtretch to the incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him into the vertuous nature, are all figurings forth of the upright righteouſneſs and godly word, who in their ſervice do go before the man, and guide him to the living book of the Lamb, which lieth hidden in<note n="(p)" place="margin">Apo. 12. a</note> the Ark of witneſs, namely within our hearts and conſciences; for there inwardly in the ſpirit, is the life of God formed, or written according to the truth.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And that ſame life of God is the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Apo. 5. a</note> book which <hi>John</hi> ſaw in his Revelation, which was full of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both without and within, and which alſo was ſhut or made faſt with ſeven ſeals, for which books ſake <hi>John</hi> wept, becauſe there was none found worthy, neither in heaven nor upon the earth, to open, to read, nor to look into the ſame book.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Howbeit in the midſt among
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:171452:82"/>
the Elders or wiſe, there ſtood a Lamb in manner as though it was killed: and he took the book unto him, and all propheſies teſtified of him with triumph and joy, ſaying, Thou<note n="(s)" place="margin">Apo. 5. d</note> art worthy to receive the book, and to open his ſeals: for thou being killed, haſt bought us with thy blood.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>John</hi> hath alſo heard a voice of many Angels,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Dan. 7. b Apo. 5. b</note> whoſe number is many thouſands of thouſands, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a mighty great voice, the the Lamb that was killed, is worthy to receive power, riches, wiſdom, ſtrength, honour, praiſe, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Behold this living book of the Lamb, is a book of ſpirit and life, and <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. a</note> not a book of the ſinful fleſh and death; for it is the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eph. 5. c Apo. 14.</note> commonalty of the Lamb in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Which Lamb is the living be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God it ſelf; the which was driven to<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 53. b 1 Pet. 2. a</note> ſuffer: and the book of life occaſioned to be ſhut<note n="(z)" place="margin">Apo. 5. a</note> with ſeven ſeals, becauſe of the great Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:171452:82"/>
which is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo. 12.</note> murderly beaſt, namely the ſelf wiſdom of the fleſh, unto<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 7. Apo 11.13. a</note> whom power hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to kill the Saints of God; but the ſame power is now even in the uttermoſt or laſt time,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apo. 17.19, 20. b</note> taken away from her; for God ſhoweth his power and dominion againſt the ſame, in the reſtoring or ſetting up again of his Saints,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eze. 37. Dan. 12. Apo. 2.</note> whom he raiſeth from the death.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Verily now it ſhall no longer prevail with the Dragon, how mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſoever the beaſt be, neither ſhall her Kingdom which is full of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations proſper any longer: for her<note n="(e)" place="margin">Apo. 18.</note> ſins are aſcended up, even unto heaven; and now ſhall her deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or fall be even into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pit.</p>
               <p n="16">16. For the ſelf-wiſdom, or ſelf-mind of the fleſh, which hath exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf very high, againſt the Lamb, even as though ſhe were Gods wiſdom,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Apo. 5.13. b</note> hath killed the Lamb from the beginning of the world and likewiſe his members the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Apo. 6.12 b 16. a</note> innocent
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:171452:83"/>
guiltleſs blood, and ſo for a time hath gotten the upper hand upon the earth; but now muſt ſhe fall and go under: whereas contrarywiſe the Saints of God ſhall<note n="(h)" place="margin">Apo.</note> raign for ever according to the Promiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:171452:83"/>
               <head>The ninteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>SEing now that the Saints of God have<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo 6.12, 13, 16.</note> ſuffered with the Lamb for a certain time, and have been killed upon the earth, therefore is the book of the beaſt moſt loved and read everywhere, &amp;<note n="(b)" place="margin">Apo. 17. b 18. a</note> men have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved according thereto; but foraſmuch as it is all now made manifeſt, through the<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. a</note> light or day of the Lord, ſo becometh the book of the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Apo. 18, 19, 20.</note> beaſt to be found a falſe book, full of deceit and ſubtile falſhood, whereunto alſo all falſe men, all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hearts of the Scripture-learned ones, and all falſe ſetters forth, and preferrers of religion, have their luſt and affection bent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For of all the names of her felfneſs or private holyneſs, and of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:171452:84"/>
all her falſe hearts and Scripture-learned ones, together with all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the heatheniſh diſtraughtneſs who do every one even joyntly with each other, ſerve and worſhip the beaſt; there is not<note n="(e)" place="margin">Apo. 13.17. a. 20, 21. b</note> one written in the living book of the Lamb; for the names of the people that ſerve and worſhip the beaſt, (whereby the Dragon hath had the dominion) are <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> all names of darkneſs, and of the good thinking wiſe, and diſobedient ones, and are all likewiſe<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Ti. 4 a</note> ſpirits of errour, as being all one, and of one manner of ſubſtance, according to one manner of nature.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That ſame verily is the cord or chain of darkneſs, or the band of the Devil, wherein all good thinking wiſe ones, and falſe hearts which do neither fear the living God of Iſrael, nor ſtand obedient to his requiring, are captived or caught, bewitched therewith, tyed thereunto, and<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. a. b. Apo. 20. b</note> led with the ſame, even into Hell; the which is the everlaſting death and damnation: from the which God
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:171452:84"/>
hath willed that the man ſhould keep himſelf, and ſerve only the living God; that<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eze 18. d</note> he might not dye, but that it might everlaſtingly go well with him, and that he might live.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The names of the people of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil &amp; wicked world,<note place="margin">The wicked world with her ſervants and fellow-companions.</note> who are written in the book of the Dragon, that murderly beaſt, are theſe, envy, diviſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention or diſcord, high-mindedneſs or pride, ſubtilty, deceit, craftineſs, unquietneſs, cruelty, arrogancy, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlyneſs, maſterfulneſs, miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veouſly diſpoſed violence, honour or vain-glory, ſtubbornneſs, reſiſtance unto Gods nature in all diſobedience, wrathfulneſs, preſumptuous boldneſs, churliſhneſs, bitterneſs, maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, commotion or uproar, treachery, ſtriving, fighting, perſecuting, lying, war or battle, vexing or troubling, curſing, ſwearing, deſtroying, ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, oppreſſing, killing, murdering, diſhoneſt dealing, unreaſonableneſs or injuſtice, gluttony, unchaſtity, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edom, adultery, knavery, bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:171452:85"/>
thievery, unprofitable ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, high vain boaſting, ambition, diſſembling, hypocriſie, Sectuariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, framed or choſen holyneſs, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, falſe God ſervices, falſe Laws, blaſphemy, ſelf-wiſdom, ſwelling in minde, curiouſneſs, ſelf-mindedneſs, unadviſedneſs, mens commandments, giving credit to the imaginations of the good thinking in the ſpirit, unbelief to the gracious word of the Lord, deſpair, doubtfulneſs, accuſing, ignorance, bondage of the heart to ſomething without the nature or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, vain comfort, ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mens fear, covetouſneſs, nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardlyneſs, undiſcreetneſs, ſcoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or mocking, diſ-favour, ſelf-Love.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There is yet moreover<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rom 1. d 1 Pet. 2. a</note> back-biting or evil reporting of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whereby to make them ſeem odious and contemptible before the people, and to cauſe themſelves to be had in favour and well-liked of.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Behold, ſuch a nature hath the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:171452:85"/>
partial Back b ter, who doth yet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes for all that, greatly bewitch the people with his abominations, as with a ſhow of holyneſs: which witchcraft is full of fooliſhneſs, and is an unprofitable deluſion, even like as are all vain games alſo, table-playing maskings or mummeries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are alſo unedifying, even like as are all manner<note n="(r)" place="margin">Eph. 5 a</note> of rude, light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, diſorderly toying, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly jeſting: all which likewiſe are names of the people of the wicked world; furthermore there is alſo death, darkneſs, falſe ſpirits, devil, hell and condemnation, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Theſe and ſuch like are the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations before God, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious miſchief, to a deſtruction over the children of men; and for one to yield or apply his heart here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, is the falling off, and the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away from God.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That is finally the perverſe and wicked nature,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Deut. 32. a. c.</note> which hath corrupted every thing, and ſtoln
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:171452:86"/>
from the man, and quite defaced in him the mind of his God, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his underſtanding, through the affection born to the knowledge of good and evil; by which manner the noble underſtanding of man is become bewitched with the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant lying being, in ſuch ſort that the man can very little underſtand<note n="(t)" place="margin">Deut, 32. Iſa. 44. Ier. 5.8. a</note> or comprehend; for it entreth too too little into the conſideration of his heart, for to come rightly to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, or turning again to his God; for be continueth even generally, cleaving faſt, and depending with his heart upon one thing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is not God; becauſe he doth not quite and clean forſake the Idols and their ſervices, nor thruſt nor chaſe them out of the Temple of his inward mind: But ſtands af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected either to this or to that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the imagination of his own underſtanding: and ſo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the God-ſervice, or God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf falſly.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:171452:86"/>9. That ſame is it verily which God hath oftentimes rebuked by the mouth of his Prophets,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa 1 b 28. b. 29. 57. b. 58. a. 59. a. b. Ier 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Eze. 5, 6. Amos 1. b Mich. 6. a</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the people of Iſrael, (when they would ſeem to turn them, and to uſe God-ſervices) did alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline their hearts towards one thing or another that was not God: and ſerved that which God never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or required.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Therefore hath God alſo in times paſt, witneſſed unto them by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> (which mind of God remaineth perpetually; for thus ſaith the Lord as an everlaſting continuing word,)</p>
               <p n="11">11. O Iſrael,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Ier. 4 a.</note> if thou wilt turn thee, then turn thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaith the Lord: And if thou wilt put away thy abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from before my face, then ſhalt thou not be caſt out: At that time ſhalt thou ſwear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and holily without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, (as true as the Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth)
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:171452:87"/>
and the heathen ſhall be bleſſed in the Lord, and make their boaſt of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:171452:87"/>
               <head>The twentieth Chapter.</head>
               <p>BUT if any one now ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in his heart, to turn him unto God, to cleave unto the Love, and to enter into the Kingdom of God; and yet for all that doth with his will, hold his heart tyed unto any thing of all the abominations above named, he doubtleſs cannot come to the Kingdom of God, nor be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly incorporated to the being of the righteous ſpirit, and of the Love, neither yet can his name be written<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apo. 5. b</note> in the living book of the Lamb, with the commonalty of the Love, which Book is in the right hand of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that liveth from everlaſting to everlaſting; which commonalty of the Love (whoſe names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:171452:88"/>
in the living book of the Lamb) is very lovely, delightful and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and with them alſo is our fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, through the Love of God the Father, and by reaſon of his mercy ſhewed on us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And with the ſame commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all thoſe likewiſe have their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, which do humble themſelves with us, under the Love and her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: and through the ſervice of Love, do hear, believe, and ſtand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the holy Doctrine and godly information, (whereby to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come underſtanding through the wiſdom and holy knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) and ſo do intirely love, exerciſe and aſſiſt the ſame ſervice of Love, for that it might be ſpread abroad ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally among many.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Howbeit, not according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones ſelf-mindedneſs, or drift of his own mind, as in a Love towards himſelf, according to his own proper knowledge,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deu 12. a</note> or good-thinking, but to come to one manner of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, under the true Love of God
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:171452:88"/>
the Father; and that altogether to an<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eph. 1. a</note> unity in the peace; alſo not with any diviſion of heart, but for to become of one mind with each other through the Love: to the end<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 57. b Luk. 10. a</note> that the peace, in that ſort might be prepared, concordable upon the earth, under the obedience of the Love, according to the Promiſes, and that all our names might be written in the book of the Lamb: and that we might be partakers of the being or nature of the ſame commonalty of Saints, whoſe names are written in that ſame Book, and might have our fellowſhip with the Lamb and his Saints.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Unto which Book of life, and his holy writings, we do humble our ſelves under the Love and her requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſo do learn of the Love the true humility, and<note n="(e)" place="margin">Math. 11. c</note> meekneſs of heart, according to the wiſdom of all thoſe whoſe names are written in the living book of the Lamb, in as much as their wiſdom only is delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto the God of life.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:171452:89"/>
                  <note place="margin">The new good world, with her ſervants and fellow-companions.</note>5. For in that ſame Book of the Lamb, (whereunto all our hope and longing ſtandeth) that it might even with fervent affection and good-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs of heart be looked into and be read by many, there is written and found therein,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Gal. 5. c Eph. 4 a Col. 3. b 1 Pet. 3. b</note> Love, peace, joy, Gods will or Law, heavenly truth, faith, righteouſneſs, meekneſs, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telneſs, friendlyneſs, long ſuffering, patience, fear of the higheſt God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. All theſe forementioned Saints have a luſt even with whole heart for to procure and prepare all thoſe which love the good life, and the everlaſting truth, unto the Love, for that they might every one become aſſembled together under the Love; and it might even ſo both inwardly and outwardly go well with all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which live under the Love, and that altogether in unpartial love.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Which upright commonalty of Saints, is not inclined to raign over one another, but to ſtand ſerviceable one towards another; and alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:171452:89"/>
all thoſe which ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with them under the obedience of the Love, becauſe that the holy underſtanding, and the knowledge of every good exerciſe, might as<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eph. 2. c 1 Pet. 2. a</note> a perfect good building, come to light, or be made manifeſt under the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the love.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Behold ſuch a nature and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſervice of unpartial love, have all thoſe, whoſe names are written in the living book of the Lamb: which ſervice ſtretcheth not to a renting and ſcattering, like as the falſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, according to the nature of the hearts of the ſelf-love, do ſtretch and have their drift thereunto, who do ſerve and live only unto themſelves, in a private mind of ſelf-love. O no; for the children of the upright Love do neither rend nor ſcatter, but ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Alſo they ſeek not<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. c</note> their ſelf-neſs, but much rather that every one might be nouriſhed and fed out of the Love and her ſervice, for to become a commodable Kingdom of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:171452:90"/>
the Love, and that the one may ſerve the other to that effect; for that is might go well with every one, and that altogether in the Love, and in the peace of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Furthermore there is written in the ſame book of the Lamb fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſightfulneſs, quietneſs, natural equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, lowlyneſs of heart, conſtancy,<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1 a</note> diſcreetneſs, meaſurableneſs, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, contentedneſs, open-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſimplicity, juſtneſs or upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, good-willingneſs,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat. 5. a 1 Tim. 1. a</note> purity of heart, clean conſcience, honeſty, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility or modeſty, obedience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſtedfaſtneſs, kind-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Phil. 4. a</note> helpfulneſs, ſerviceableneſs to the vertue, peaceable converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Gods praiſe, laud, glory, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and heavenly delightfulneſs, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Now for to have our fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the ſame commonalty of the upright Saints of God,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ge. 1.2. b</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto doubtleſs was the man created from the beginning, becauſe that ſuch a precious excellency, and ſuch a
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:171452:90"/>
Kingly Crown of delightful beauty ſhould have the dominion over him.</p>
               <p n="12">12. For thoſe ſame and all they which are like unto them of nature and diſpoſition, their names verily are every one written in the living Book of the Lamb, who do neither worſhip, honour, or ſerve the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Apo. 13. a</note> Dragon, or the high-minded beaſt: for the name of the moſt high God is written upon them, which God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they do<note n="(q)" place="margin">Apo. 7. b. 21, 22. a</note> ſerve, honour, and worſhip from everlaſting to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: they ſtand all likewiſe as lights of life, in the beholding of God their Father.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Behold that ſame holy people of God or Chriſt, (or ſuch like) is the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 64. a</note> houſe of Iſrael,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Eph. 2. b.</note> the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen-ſhip of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Love, and they are every one likewiſe the true<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iſa. 66. b</note> children of Sion, where the God of life hath his holy Tabernacle, in whom<note n="(u)" place="margin">Lev. 16. 2 Cor. 6. b</note> he dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, liveth, and walketh: And they ſhall be the Lords people for ever
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:171452:91"/>
and ever. And he himſelf, God with them will be their God, and<note n="(x)" place="margin">Apo. 21. a</note> wipe away all tears from their eyes, and will put away<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 61. a</note> their contempt from them; they ſhall alſo ſerve the ſtrange nations no more, but only the Lord their God.</p>
               <p n="14">14. They have doubtleſs been conſtrained a long time to ſuffer with the Lamb, for the wickedneſs and ignorances cauſe of the people, but now<note n="(z)" place="margin">Baruch 5. b</note> doth the Lord bring them again with joy, that they may rejoyce them in the holy Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, even as it beſeemeth the children of light to do, who do rejoyce them only in their God.</p>
               <p n="15">15. This verily is the bleſſing, which was publiſhed and affirmed unto all generations of the earth, according to the Promiſes; for that they might be all ſaved, through the Love of God the Father: which bleſſing and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they do all now obtain, if they do believe the word of
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:171452:91"/>
truth, and ſtand good of will, and humble them under the Love and her ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:171452:92"/>
               <head>The one and twentieth Chapter.</head>
               <p>BEhold and conſider ye dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, both theſe forms, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or beings, which are here figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or ſet forth unto you, before your eyes, even according to the life: namely the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 1 a Apo. 9.12.13. a.</note> murderly ſeed of the high-minded beaſt, or the names of the people that are her members, which do raign in the perditionable world, which is full of blood-guilty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the innocents; and alſo the names of the people of Iſrael, or houſe of Love, the high commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:171452:92"/>
ſeed of the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Apo. 7. a. b 14, 15, 19. a</note> benignity or loving kindneſs of the Lamb; the which hath even hitherto,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apo. 6 b.</note> kept and born the patience with the Lamb becauſe of the wicked.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Verily the houſe of Iſrael, or the commonalty of the Love, the elected Saints of God, do follow after Chriſt their King, even<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ro. 6. a. c</note> unto their death, and alſo to the life: for they do in like manner bear the croſs of the Lamb, and therein keep the word of his patience: They likewiſe, even according to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Lamb, do ſhew a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obedience,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Phil. 2 a</note> till unto the death; (namely unto the death of the Croſs) whereby to obtain the dominion with the Lamb over the ſin, death, hell, condemnation, and the world, to the end they might in like manner, through the Lamb, and the death of his croſs, keep the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. f</note> all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p n="3">3. With which Saints of the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:171452:93"/>
and upright being, the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 60, 61, 62. 2 Pet. 3. b</note> now coming or new world, ſhall alſo be inhabited in a perfect delight of God, in all Love, in<note n="(h)" place="margin">Eph. 4 a</note> unity of peace, and in upright righteouſneſs and holyneſs which God eſteemeth of: But the ungodly ſhall periſh or weare away out of the Land of the living, for that the Land may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited in reſt and peace, and with triumph and joy for evermore, to the laud and praiſe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Therefore O all ye people, look now into both theſe forms, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and beings: and chooſe either the one or the other of them, whom ye will incline unto, whether it be<note n="(i)" place="margin">Deut. 30. Ier. 21. a Eccleſ. 15.</note> the death or the life, the Devil or God, the old wicked world, or the new upright world, and then cleave only to the ſame, to the end that ye may ſever your ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and ſo expreſs thereby with whom ye do hold or ſtand
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:171452:93"/>
agreeably minded, or what ye do love,<note n="(k)" place="margin">3 Kin. 18.</note> and halt no longer on both ſides.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If therefore you will incline or cleave to the Lamb, or that ye look into or eſteem his being to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a godly being, then love the ſame with a ſingle and humble heart, ſtanding ſubmitted to rhe Love, and ſo depart out of the death, into the life: put your truſt in God, in your proceeding on to the ſame life,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ioh. 5. c Rom. 6.8. b</note> and ſtand firm in the hope of your ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But if ye be yet young or weak and unable for to live in the good, or if ye be yet over-maſtered by the evil, againſt your will, for God is both reaſonable and courteous: and if the man be of a good will, then doth God require no more, but that the man will ſtill remain ſtedfaſt in the ſame good will: for unto ſuch a good willing man, doth he<note n="(m)" place="margin">Phil. 1.2. b</note> bring his power and ſtrength, for that the man ſhould with the ſame
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:171452:94"/>
obtain through Faith, and that in a ſuffering manner, the righteouſneſs againſt the ſin.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Therefore poſſeſs your ſouls with<note n="(n)" place="margin">Luk. 21. c</note> patience, reſt believing, and continue in the hope; and ye ſhall aſſuredly, in the patience evidently perceive, that the evil waxeth weak, and that your ſoul ſhall be ſound or whole.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Shew or let it alwayes appear what ye love; namely the good or the evil, for look what one hunteth after, that he catcheth: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever one loveth, of that he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear ſome ſpeech or tydings, and he is deſirous alſo to be with the ſame for no man would willingly be ſeparated from his beſt beloved: therefore judge your own ſelves now, and look rightly into your ſelves according to the truth, to note what ye love, and with what ye would willingly be, and have your fellowſhip, namely<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 8. b</note> with the good being of God, or with the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:171452:94"/>
pernitious and naughty Being of the wicked and deceitful world.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If now therefore ye love and ſtand inclined unto the good being:<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſa. 34.13. d Amos 5 b</note> then forſake the evil or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly being and ſeparate your ſelves quite and clean with all your will,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſa. 52. 2 Cor. 6. Apo. 18.</note> from the evil or ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, departing out of the ſame, from day to day, and be patient in the hope, till that all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly being do go under and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or conſume to nothing in you.</p>
               <p n="10">10. This is our Croſs, which<note n="(s)" place="margin">Math. 10. d. 16. c Luk 9.14</note> we ought daily to take up, in the belief: And ſo in that manner to follow after the vertue of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs: Alſo to love the wiſdom and the Information, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the chaſtiſement<note n="(t)" place="margin">Prov. 3 b Heb. 12. a</note> or corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Lord, that meeteth with us, the whileſt our hearts are yet captivated with the ſin and<note n="(u)" place="margin">Eph. 4. b</note> blindneſs.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Behold even ſuch (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:171452:95"/>
as of meer Love we have te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified herein) is the right way to the God of life, and to his righteouſneſs, from the which<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal. 14. Sap. 5. Rom. 2. b</note> the man is departed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged: In which way the man being in his eſtranging from his God, is by<note n="(y)" place="margin">Eph. 2. a</note> Gods grace cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and bidden to come again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his God, through the belief or confidence in God, touching the ſalvation; to the end he ſhould according to the truth, know his God in the life, and ſo might worſhip<note n="(z)" place="margin">Deut. 4. a 10. b Math. 4. c</note> and ſerve him only, which<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 14 b Acts 14. Apo. 14.</note> hath made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, the Sea and the water Fountains: through whoſe power the elements be moved; and out of whom the upright wiſdom of the wiſe, the true light of the illuminated ones, and the reſurrection of the righteous life ſpringeth, which God is alſo the perfection, the Love,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioh. 17. c 1 Ioh. 4. b</note> or the true being or eſſential power
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:171452:95"/>
it ſelf, unto whom only apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth all praiſe, laud, honour for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Take it to heart.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:96"/>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:171452:96"/>
            <head>A PRAYER OF <hi>H. N.</hi> Even as he hath prayed the ſame unto Almighty God, through the holy ſpirit of love, according to the eſtate and repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the fallen man, corrupt and earthly weak man.</head>
            <p>O God who liveſt for ever, thou which in times paſt waſt a
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:171452:97"/>
comfort to the ſorrowful in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, laid on them through the dominion of the violent power of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and didſt<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exo. 3. 12, 13, 14. Pſa. 78. b. f</note> lead thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of the power of his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, delivering them from the hand of thoſe that cruelly raigned over them: and didſt ſhew, how that thou wert a Judge over thy flock, which thou hadſt choſen to thy ſelf: making known unto them<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ex. 20.34. Deut. 5.10.30.</note> what thy will was: and didſt ſet up among them the banner of righteouſneſs; (namely<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ex 35.40.</note> the Tabernacle of thy Sanctuary) and madeſt thy holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation amongſt them, and didſt not ſuffer them to want any thing, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as thou hadſt ſaid unto their Fathers, and promiſed unto them by the mouth of thy holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And unto the heathen which knew not thy holy name, thou<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 11 13. Ro. 9 11.15.</note> haſt alſo in times paſt ſhewed thy mercy, according to the Covenant of thy holy Promiſes, which thou hadſt
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:171452:97"/>
made with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Now therefore O God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, comfort us likewiſe in our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, for thy<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa. 38. b</note> holy names ſake: for when thou makeſt up thy ſelf to raign over thine enemies, then muſt they all be affraid, and bow down themſelves before the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power of thy Almighty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But we O God are well wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of thy chaſtiſement<note n="(f)" place="margin">Deu. 27.28. Dan. 9.</note> for our ſins cauſe; for in all theſe thy former works, proceeded out of the entire or hearty mercifulneſs of thy love borne towards us, we have ſhewed our ſelves to be an unthankful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, declining from thy word of life, and like an ungodly people, have eſtranged our ſelves from thy truth, walking in error,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 1. c</note> according to the mind of our own delight, and been ignorant in that thing thy will requireth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But now O Lord which art the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:171452:98"/>
God of all the world,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 106. Ier. 14. Lam 3. Dan. 9.</note> we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſs our own of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and alſo the falling away of our Fathers and ſeeking daily for thy wayes, we do enquire what thy will is.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wherefore O God, remember now thy mercy, like as in times paſt, and thy Covenant which thou haſt made with thy people in times paſt, and turn thee again unto us, that thou mayeſt be known among all people, as an eternal true God of life and of righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="7">7. O how often is my heart grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved becauſe that there is neither<note n="(i)" place="margin">Hoſ 4.</note> faithfulneſs nor love, or at leaſt wiſe very little anywhere to be found, and for that the righteouſneſs is ſo utterly turned back<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 59. b</note> or refuſed in all places</p>
            <p n="8">8. Oh what a number of diſeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note n="(l)" place="margin">Iſa. 1. a</note> and wounded ones are there, and how many are there that do now mourn, yea ſuffer grief and wofulneſs or anguiſh, becauſe<note n="(m" place="margin">4 Eſd. 5.14, 15. Math 24. b.</note> the iniquity
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:171452:98"/>
raigneth ſo exceedingly, and for that the number of the upright and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ones are ſo few.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Oh how long ſhall my ſoul reſt in longing after that whereunto my heart hath a luſt, and whereunto it is drawn or inflamed with fervent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Oh where abideth now the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Iſ 60, 61. Mal. 4. a</note> riſing up of thy glory, O thou pure love of God the Father, wherein all peace, truth, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and righteouſneſs ſtandeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</p>
            <p n="11">11. I have ſeen thee afar off, and alſo neer by,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Cant. 4.5.</note> thou haſt peirced me through with the bright beams of thy upright righteouſneſs, and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able delightfulneſs: but my ſoul ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth ſo much the more grief, for my ſpirit cannot be ſatisfied, ſo long as thou only haſt not the upper hand or dominion over us: and that we do not with our mind approach or draw neer unto thee eſſentially, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come incorporated wholly, or in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:171452:99"/>
every part unto thy being and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p n="12">12. For we find by experience, that without thee, O pure Love, there is no bread of ſatisfying,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Iſa 41.45 Ier. 14. a</note> nor any water of refreſhing; becauſe all delectable ſweetneſs is contained in thee.</p>
            <p n="13">13. In thee is milk and hony, wine and<note n="(q)" place="margin">Hoſ. 2. Ioel 2.</note> oyl, alſo riches, joy and life.</p>
            <p n="14">14. In thee are likewiſe<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 33. Epheſ. 3. Col. 2.</note> all treaſures of wiſdom, the holy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſecretneſs of God, and the myſterie of the Chriſt of God: for Chriſt is at thy right hand, as a living ſalvation, for all thoſe that come unto thee.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Whoſoever alſo ſeeketh Chriſt without thee,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Joh. 7. d</note> he ſhall not find him; and whoſoever hath not thee, he hath neither Law of righteouſneſs, nor yet Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Therefore art thou likewiſe O Love, the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Ioh. 13, 14, 15. 1 Tim. 1. 1 Ioh. 4.</note> band of perfection, wherein all ſalvation conſiſteth, and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:171452:99"/>
the laſt ſign or token of the true righteouſneſs wherein all Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have witneſſed.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Alſo no man cometh<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.9.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, except thou draw him, for thou O Love art the fountain of all vertue.</p>
            <p n="18">18. But who are thoſe that love thee? thou allureſt all men doubtleſs; but who yieldeth himſelf to be drawn by thee? thou<note n="(x)" place="margin">Apo 3. c</note> knockeſt daily, but who letteth thee in?<note n="(y)" place="margin">Prov 1. c Iſa. 65, 66. a</note> thou calleſt indeed, but who heareth thee? thou ſayeſt,</p>
            <p n="19">19. Come hither to this<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſa. 55.</note> water, all ye that are thirſty, ye which have no mony, come buy both wine and milk; Come buy, that ye may have to eat of free-coſt, and not for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney nor ware. Wherefore beſtow ye your money for that which feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not? and your labour for that which any way ſatisfies not? Hearken unto me, ſo ſhall ye eat of the beſt, and your ſoul ſhall have a delight in the fatneſs or plenty; incline your ears
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:171452:100"/>
hitherward, and come unto me, hearken, ſo ſhall your ſoul be heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="20">20. O God who thinketh upon this, that thy Promiſes are that we ſhould be aſſembled unto thee in the Love,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> whereby to know thee as a true God, which liveth everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
            <p n="21">21. For thou O God art a God that loveſt the very beſt of the fruits of the field, and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Exod. 13.34. Le. 1, 2, 3. Deut. 12.14.</note> haſt a delight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fat of the Sheep and Lambs, as it is a burnt-offering unto thee of a ſweet Savour, upon thy<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 43. Iſa. 56.</note> holy Altar in thy Tabernacle of thy dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which thou haſt choſen unto thy ſelf,<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Par. 6. a. 7. b</note> in thy holy City <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. But thou<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa. 57.65</note> deſpiſeſt all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations offered in Forrein Lands, as likewiſe all God-ſervices upon their mountains and upon all their hills and high-places.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Thou alſo rejecteſt<note n="(f)" place="margin">Amos 5.</note> all ſongs of praiſe, uſed under their
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:171452:100"/>
trees, and under all their green eaves.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Thou abhorreſt all preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous arrogancy of the fleſh: they do all diſpleaſe thee, which ſeek thee through their own doings, to the end to be at one with thee, and yet have no regard unto thy Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Their God-ſervice is<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 16.43 Amos 5. Hoſ. 5.6.</note> an abomination unto thee: their ſelf-Sanctification (although the fleſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſeth it ſelf therewith) doth alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſtink before thee.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Unto their Sabboths, Holy-dayes, or ſelf-made reſt-dayes, thou haſt no deſire or liking.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Their prayer alſo cometh not before thine ears,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Prov. 11 Iſa. 1.59. Mich 3 4 Eſd. 3.</note> as that it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thee any whit at all. For it is all filthy before thee, if they ſeek thee without thy Promiſes: For they ſeek not thee O God, but themſelves, and how to pleaſe themſelves.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Their waies that they walk, lead not unto thee: But they run
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:171452:101"/>
apace towards Hell, and have a luſt unto error.</p>
            <p n="29">29. There is nothing among them, but manly fear, and ſnaring of the heart with captivated conſciences, according to the old cuſtom of the vain heathen, which, O God, knew not thy wayes; but upon their own wiſdom and ſelf-made wayes, they<note n="(i)" place="margin">Iſa. 3. b</note> are proud and very bold.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Therefore is not likewiſe<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa 59. b</note> the right knowledge of their ſin among them, as to account the ſame for ſin; that they might turn them unto thee, becauſe they know not O God of thy peace, nor underſtand rightly any thing thereof.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Thy rebuke and chaſtionable information, have they not rightly felt, neither alſo rightly taken heed to the ſame, nor yet underſtood what thou intendeſt therein, and requireſt therewith; therefore doubtleſs the right fear of God is not before their eyes, like as the fear of men is, for to pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:171452:101"/>O God plant thy<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 40. Iſa. 51. Jer. 31. d</note> Law in their hearts, as a Glaſs or a clear light unto their inwardneſs; then ſhall they rightly know their ſin;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Rom. 7. d</note> how or in what manner ſhe is ſin, to the end that ſin may make up her ſelf, and ſhew in what form ſhe is the fruits of death, or the deadly being (the which ſhe eſtrangteh the man from the living God-head) for that the ſin thereby may be conſumed<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Co. 15. f</note> (for thy Law is an encountring or enveighing power againſt the ſin) and then ſhall they know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whom they ought to fear, and cleave unto.</p>
            <p n="33">33. For when as thy Law O God, groweth up in us, in our earthly and weak man-hood, and requireth thy righteouſneſs of us, then are we bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and grieved, wherethrough we grow to diſcern our fall from thee, and the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 51. a</note> great abundance of our ſins, and that likewiſe it is all ſin, wherein we are conceived, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have lived.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:171452:102"/>34. Yea that which in times paſt we ſuppoſed to be good, is now found to be meer wickedneſs and ſin: by reaſon whereof our ſouls become humbled before thee, for to obtain mercy from thee out of thy abundant grace: Even then alſo do we confeſs, what we are according to our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manhood, (namely,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Gen. 2. b Eccl. 10 17. b</note> duſt, earth and aſhes) and that we of our ſelves being without the effect or eſtate of thy Love, are altogether<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſ. 14.53 a Rom 3. b</note> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and lying, and utterly eſtranged from thy righteouſneſs: And ſo with lowly hearts, by reaſon of the depth of our neceſſity or extremity for the ſins cauſe, we become then O God rightly turned unto thee, whereby through the drawing or allurement of thy Love to come again unto thee.</p>
            <p n="35">35. By means of which humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or abaſing of our ſelves, we through thy grace and mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come endowed by thee with the moſt holy belief, through the which
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:171452:102"/>
we be then likewiſe baptized or waſhed in the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Rom 6 Gal. 3. Col 2.</note> death of Chriſt, and do ſtand firm in the hope, to the obtaining of the health of our ſouls, and ſo through the belief, miniſtred under the obedience of thy Love, we become made<note n="(s)" place="margin">Rom. 8. a.</note> free from the Law of ſin and death, by the ſpirit of thy Law which maketh alive in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="36">36. Oh how far is the man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted and eſtranged from the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right knowledge of this wiſdom of God.</p>
            <p n="37">37. O God, that my heart might rent open it ſelf, and might cry unto thee with a forcible courage; And that thou wouldeſt hearken to my voice, and wouldeſt vouchſafe to look down towards us with thy merciful eyes; and take compaſſion of our miſery, deformity and fall, and over the blindneſs of our errors, and wouldeſt in chaſtionable manner draw us unto thee, that we might rightly convert or come again and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:171452:103"/>
live in thee: For we are doubtleſs, fallen, eſtranged, and ſtrayed very deep, and far from thee and thy Chriſt, we have mingled our ſelves with the ſtrangers, and walked in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errors.</p>
            <p n="38">38. O God, let us in every part ſee into our<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iob 13. Pſa. 14. Iſa. 59.</note> tranſgreſſing, and make known unto us the lying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our hearts againſt thee.</p>
            <p n="39">39. For many do ſay, It is very good, whereas doubtleſs it is meer evil: And they ſay moreover out of the blindneſs and ignorance of their hearts, Behold<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ier. 8 a Math. 24. b</note> here is the holy Scripture, we have the right or the truth, the being of God, and the holy Ghoſt: And alſo the mind and ſenſe of the wiſdom, for to underſtand the ſame; we have the true belief in Chriſt, and are the Lords people. O God they ſpeak lyes before thine ears, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not the counſel of thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but are children of the fall
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:171452:103"/>
or tranſgreſſion; among whom there is neither being of God, nature of thy love, nor belief of thy Chriſt; but only a vain and falſe boaſting, whereby they ſeduce both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others more; for they oppreſs the little ones and the poor, and reſiſt thy holy ſervice of Love; therefore one may eaſily find many maſters and vaunters, but very few ſervants, and yet<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. b</note> many fewer Fathers in the Office of the Love.</p>
            <p n="40">40. Oh that many of them ſaw their vain wiſdom, whereon they boaſt ſo highly; and that they knew their miſery; then would they alſo out of meer neceſſity cry<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſa. 130. a</note> unto God for his grace, that they might come again to the life of Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="41">41. Now O Lord and God be mindful of us, extend thy mercy over us,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Tob. 3. a</note> and revenge thee not on us, for our ſins cauſe.</p>
            <p n="42">42. Remember not<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 79. a</note> O God
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:171452:104"/>
our offences and ignorance, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſ. 103 b</note> we are duſt, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without thy being, are nothing <note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 3. Eccl. 10. b 17. d</note> but earth and aſhes; for all our beauty, or ſelf-choſen wiſdom or righteouſneſs,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 40 a. 1 Pet. 1. c</note> muſt wither away like unto the flowers or graſs of the field; And all whatſoever is not of thy being, muſt be conſumed and brought to nothing in<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eccl. 1. a</note> the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of humiliation or abaſing, wherein our tryal cometh to paſs; but thy righteouſneſs, word, will and<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 33. a 119. 2. Iſa. 40.4. b</note> wiſdom continueth for ever.</p>
            <p n="43">43. O Lord thou Almighty God, which art the Father, procreator or begetter of all generations, ſhew thy mercy upon thine own handy-work, namely on thoſe that labour daily to do thy will.</p>
            <p n="44">44. Open unto us with thy light, <note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſa. 13. a</note> the eyes of our ſpirit, and ſhew thy grace on us, we blind people, who yet notwithſtanding have eyes: unſtop unto us with thy underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:171452:104"/>
the ears of our inwardneſs, even of us deaf people, who yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have ears: to<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 6. Math. 13. Acts 28.</note> the end that we may rightly hear thy word, believe the ſame, and underſtand and obey it according to thy truth: and turn about or<note n="(i)" place="margin">4 Kin. 22 Eze. 11.18.36</note> mollifie the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our hearts, with thy meekneſs, that we may humbly and obediently, with all good-willingneſs, turn us rightly unto thee, and to the Love of Chriſt and be ſaved: And may<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ioh. 17. c</note> alſo become one with thy holy word, like as thou thy ſelf O God, art one with the ſame: wheteby the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Num. 14. c</note> world may become full of thy glory, and that thy Chriſt may appear and bear ſway over all, in all, and with all, and that we all may be one in thee: and may<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ioh. 17. b</note> know in the truth that thou only art a very true God: for to that end, becauſe the world ſhould know and underſtand the ſame, haſt thou ſent thy Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="45">45. Now O God, ſtrengthen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, the office of thy Love, for that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:171452:105"/>
all thoſe which hope on thee, and love thy righteouſneſs, may be drawn into one<note n="(n)" place="margin">Col. 3. b</note> band of Love, and that thou mighteſt be the head over us all, as a God and King over all power and Lordſhip: and that we all from<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ier. 31. Heb. 8. b</note> the leaſt even unto the greateſt may know and acknowledge thee, according to the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p n="46">46. Therefore is likewiſe our flight for refuge O God only unto thee, and unto the requiring of thy ſervice of Love, whereby to find grace at thy hands, that thou mayeſt raign over us: and for<note n="(p)" place="margin">Par. 36.</note> that cauſe do we daily bow the knees of our hearts before thee, and pray and make ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication unto thee in the ſpirit; O God be thou gracious and merciful unto us.</p>
            <p n="47">47. Be thou our Shepheard, King, and Prince, and remember Lord thy Covenant, and<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſa. 64. a b</note> Sanctuary that hath a long time lain waft and been ſpoiled.</p>
            <p n="48">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:171452:105"/>48. Awake O Lord<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſa. 35. c</note> with thy ſpirit over us; for all the comfort of man is vain,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 62.118.146. a Ier. 17. a</note> all confidence and ſtay on Princes is nothing in it ſelf:<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iſa. 4. b</note> the Prophets ſeduce and deceive,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ier. 5.8.23, 27, 29.</note> the Seers do fail in the right: the worldly wiſe and Scripture-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned do preach lyes: The Prieſts do deal with falſe God-ſervices, the Judges give Sentence even as the Princes do require it,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 1. c Ier. 5. Eze. 22. Ioh. 3.</note> the world is repleniſhed with traytorie; the common people do deal with crafty deceipts: unto the poor and miſerable people there happeneth wrong and violence everywhere: and the Lands are full of innocent blood-guiltyneſs.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Therefore look down, O God, look down, and ſanctifie thy great name, and teach us thy Law, Statutes and Rights, that they may all know that they be but men: and that thou O Lord art God only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom alſo<note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Tim 1. b</note> all honour, praiſe and laud, doth only belong and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain.</p>
            <p n="50">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:171452:106"/>50. Wherefore ſhould the<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.47.</note> heathen ſtill blaſpheme thy Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? and why ſhould our enemies, with the Arrogancy of their minds, and vain perſwaſions, ſay that thou O God art with them, and minded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their will? boaſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in arrogancy, that their inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious wit and prudence ſhall keep the upper hand or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</p>
            <p n="51">51. O God, haſt not thou from the beginning foreſeen thy Chriſt to be a head<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph 1.3. b</note> and Father, over all, and in all: and elected him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto before the foundation of the world was laid? yea to that end alſo thou<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioh. 3. d</note> haſt loved him,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 11. c Luk. 10. c</note> and given him all what is thine, for that<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 9. a Luk. 1. d</note> he might poſſeſs the ſeat of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and be a King over the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p n="52">52. Is not he alſo ordained to be a reſtoring to the houſe of Iſrael,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 15. a</note> whereby to eſtabliſh the Promiſes
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:171452:106"/>
made to their Fathers? hath not he likewiſe called and bidden the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thereunto?<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſa. 57. Luk. 2. Eph. 2. b</note> Is not the peace publiſhed through Chriſt? Hath not he in holyneſs of heart, loved faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſa. 81. Hoſ. 2. c</note> and truth? hath not he alſo taught<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat. 11.18. a</note> humility, and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart? Have not his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers preached and publiſhed the Love to<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Co. 13. a Col. 3. b</note> be a bond of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? But oh where is all this! where ſhall men find the ſame?</p>
            <p n="53">53. O God, prepare the hearts of the people unto lowlyneſs, that they may ſtand ſubmitted to the Love in all humility, and may love the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="(k)" place="margin">Matth. 24.25. d 1 Cor. 1 a</note> of thy Chriſt in his glory; by whom the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Tit. 2. b Acts 17. d</note> univerſal earth ſhall be judged with righteouſneſs, who likewiſe ſhall diſturb or trouble all authority and power, and bring it under his obedience, and then reſign or yield up the<note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. c</note> Kingdom, all power and dominion unto thee
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:171452:107"/>
O Almighty God, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be all in all.</p>
            <p n="54">54. O God put this into the hearts of all Governors or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to look into and conſider of: and illuminate all Kings, Princes, Lords, and Potentates or Rulers, with thy godly wiſdom, that they may fear thy holy name, ſtand ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thy Love and her ſervice, and turn them away from all violence and abuſe: And that the world may to thy praiſe, be inhabited in the Love and in all truth, and all men become turned unto thee,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Exo 18.33. Math 3. Luk. 3 a</note> in true repentance for their ſins: and the horrible plagues of ungodlyneſs, which are<note n="(o)" place="margin">Apo. 18. a</note> come over the world for the ſins cauſe, might ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="55">55. O God let us now find grace before thine eyes, like as in times paſt, the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ioh 3. b</note> City of <hi>Nineveh</hi> did, on the which thou ſhewedſt mercy, that we do not all periſh,<note n="(q)" place="margin">4 Eſd. 2 2 Pet 2. a</note> like unto <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> for
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:171452:107"/>
our ſins, are become many, and grown to be<note n="(r)" place="margin">3 Eſd. 8. b</note> abundant, even beyond all meaſure.</p>
            <p n="56">56. O Lord and God, O heavenly Father, give ear I beſeech thee to the crying of the poor,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſa. 25.27.86. b</note> and lead us in thy wayes, gather us together on thy pathes, and unite our hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note n="(t)" place="margin">Col. 3. b</note> one band of Love,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ioh. 17. c</note> as one in all, and all in one, with love, equity and righteouſneſs; and cleanſe our<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſa. 51. b Eze. 36.</note> minds from all ungodly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or nature, and deſtroy or break in ſunder,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſa. 1.33.</note> all ungodly counſel, that iniquity may not raign for ever.</p>
            <p n="57">57. For, wherefore ſhould the darkneſs poſſeſs thine inheritance; and ſtill unhallow and lay waſt thy holy place, Temple, or Tabernacle? Should the houſe of the Devil alſo ſtill be builded, and thy houſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly city continue waſte, and ruinated more and more?</p>
            <p n="58">58. O God, behold how that the <note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſa. 64. c</note> dwelling of thy Sanctuary, lyeth
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:171452:108"/>
overthrown and deſtroyed, for in thy Temple<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lam. 4. Matth. 24. a Luk. 19. c</note> there is not one ſtone that remaineth ſtanding one upon another, but are all broken and ſcattered from each other; and upon the holy place of thy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary are now the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 9. Matth. 24. Mark. 13. b</note> abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of deſolation raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="59">59. O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou City of Peace, of the great and mighty King, how art thou grown<note n="(c)" place="margin">Lam. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> now to ſuppreſſion and contempt, when ſhalt thou yet, O thou holy City, be repaired or <note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 58. c 61. a</note> builded up again to an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtability, and receive thy peaceable children of Iſrael into thy dwelling!</p>
            <p n="60">60. O Sion, thou hill of pure Beauty, when ſhall thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as alſo the Heathens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iding thee have an end! And when ſhalt thou, O forſaken one, be comforted again, to<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa. 49.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 66.</note> the end that thou which haſt a long
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:171452:108"/>
time been unfruitful, mighteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fruitful again: and that thy dried up breſts might give forth their milk again;<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſa. 61. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that Kings might ſuck thy breſts, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel Lords learn thy peace, thy children dwell at Jeruſalem, and rejoyce their in thee O Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</p>
            <p n="61">61. But when as I now O Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and Sion, do think upon thy contempt and ſuppreſſion, then doth my ſoul ſuffer<note n="(g)" place="margin">La. 1.2. c</note> great ſorrow and grief for thy ſake; and mine eyes guſh over with tears, for very pitty and compaſſion ſake towards thee, that thou haſt ſo long time layn waſt and ſuppreſt.</p>
            <p n="62">62. But when I think upon the Promiſes, touching thy reſtoring, and upon<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 54.60, 61, 62.</note> the garniſhing of beauty, which is coming unto thee O Jerſuſalem and Sion, in holyneſs and righteouſneſs; and that thy children ſhall be taught by
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:171452:109"/>
the<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ier 31. d Ioh. 6. a</note> Lord, then doth my ſoul refreſh or comfort her ſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</p>
            <p n="63">63. For the Law ſhall<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 2. a Mich. 4. a</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of Sion, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem; He ſhall come from thence, which ſhall turn away<note n="(l)" place="margin">Iſa. 59. Rom. 11. Ioel 2, 3.</note> ungodlyneſs from <hi>Jacob,</hi> that the children of <hi>Iacob</hi> may have their dwelling at Jeruſalem for ever, according to the Promiſes.</p>
            <p n="64">64. For the Lords Election is at Jeruſalem,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa. 78.87. Iſa. 2. Mich. 4.</note> and even there upon the Hill of Sion hath God foreſeen him an holy houſe, which ſhall be exalted above all hills or high places, becauſe that his name may ſtill be worſhipped there, and that<note n="(n)" place="margin">Iſa. 56. a Mal. 1.3 a</note> his offering may alwayes and for evermore be offered there: for his houſe which he hath choſen to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat 21. b</note> a houſe of Prayer and of holy offering.</p>
            <p n="65">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:171452:109"/>65. An upright mind towards thee, in our inwardneſs,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſa. 34.51. Iſa. 57.66.</note> A contrite heart, and a lowly ſpirit, ſhalt not thou O God deſpiſe: For thou wilt enter into the ſame, alſo make thy<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ioh. 14. c</note> dwelling even there, and ſanctifie thy name from generation to generation, for evermore, it is very true.</p>
            <p>Take it to heart.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Charitas extorſit per</hi> H. N.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:110"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171452:110"/>
            <head>Of the Eight VERTVES OR Godlyneſſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Vertues or Godlyneſſes do proceed or ſpring.</head>
            <p n="1">1. MY beloved, Here have I out of the Love of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, witneſſed and ſet forth unto
<pb facs="tcp:171452:111"/>
you eight Vertues or Godlyneſſes, and poſſeſs or endow you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal, or leave the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd for you, as a good Teſtament to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Memorial o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Remembrance.<note place="margin">Deut. 30.31.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For that cauſe is alſo my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation heartily unto you all, that ye would continually with diligence give your endeavor to enſue or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after the ſame eight Vertues or Godlyneſſes, and to exerciſe your ſelves therein obediently, and even ſo according to the requiring of the holy and gratious word of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of the Love of Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 83. Eph 4. Col. 3.</note> proceed and grow forth from the one Vertue or Godlyneſs unto another: For out of the ſame eight Vertues or Godlyneſſes proceedeth or ſpringeth all upright righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, love and peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For that cauſe let all your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe be for to live and and walk in the ſame going forth from the one Vertue or Godlyneſs into another,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.30, 31. Pſal, 83.</note> till unto the perfecteſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The firſt Vertue or the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:171452:111"/>
of the ſame eight Vertues or Godlyneſſes, is the Luſt, Pleaſure or the Will of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For which Luſts cauſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1.</note> or Will of the Lord becauſe the ſame might obtain an eſſential ſhape in you) ye ſhall altogether forſake,<note place="margin">Math. 16. Mark. 8.</note> hate and leave all your own luſts, pleaſures and will, and give over your ſelves wholly to the Luſt or Will of the Lord,<note place="margin">Luk. 9:14. Ioh. 12. Math. 26.39. Mark. 14.36. Luk. 22.42,</note> and to the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame, for to live and walk obediently, only according to the Lords Luſt or Will, according to the Ordinance of the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame, for to live &amp; walk obediently only according to the Lords luſt or will, according to the Ordinance of the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When ye now are well exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſame firſt Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, ſo ſhall ye then proceed in the next Vertue or Godlyneſs.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Which next Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs is the holy Law or requiſite Ordinance of the Lord, becauſe that
<pb facs="tcp:171452:112"/>
ye might love the Lord your God in his Law or Ordinance with all your hearts and thoughts, and your neighbour as your ſelf.</p>
            <p n="8">8. For which Laws cauſe, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.50. Math. 22.37.</note> (becauſe the ſame might obtain a being-like ſhape in you) ye ſhall altogether forſake,<note place="margin">Mark. 12.30. Rom. 13.8.</note> hate and leave your own ſelves and your own Law or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and all your Love to the ſame and to your own ſelves,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.8. Deut. 10. Deut. 4.</note> and even ſo altogether give over your ſelves to the Law or Ordinance of the Lord, as to his Love, and to the Law of your neighbour, and to the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame Law or Ordinance of the Lord, for to live and walk obediently, only in the Law or Ordinance of the Lord &amp; in his Love, as alſo the Love of your neighbour, &amp; in the ordinance of the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When ye now are well exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this ſame ſecond Vertue or Godlyneſs, ſo ſhall ye then proceed in the third Vertue or Godlyneſs.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb facs="tcp:171452:112"/>10. Which Vertue or Godlyneſs is then Righteouſnes of God,<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> or the members of the body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="11">11. For which righteouſneſs ſake of God or body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> becauſe that ye might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated as fellow members of the ſame righteouſneſs of God or body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Amos:</note> might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain even to a being-like ſhape in you,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4, 5.</note> ye ſhall altogether forſake your ſelves, and all your own or choſen righteouſneſs or holyneſs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> which ye have without the righteouſneſs and co-defied holyneſs of God, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the body of Jeſus Chriſt, and hate and leave the ſame,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> and even ſo altogether give over your ſelves to the righteouſneſs of God, or body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> and to the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame body of Jeſus Chriſt or righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.</note> for to live and walk obediently only in the Equity, and upright righteouſneſs and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the righteouſneſs of God,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> or
<pb facs="tcp:171452:113"/>
body of Jeſus Chriſt, and in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="12">12. When ye now are incorporated to this ſame 3. Vertue or Godlyneſs, and well exerciſed in the ſame,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.</note> then ſhall ye proceed in the fourth Vertue r Godlyneſs.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Which fourth Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, is the Lordlyneſs or Dominion of God, or eſſentially to Lord with God.</p>
            <p n="14">14. For the which Lordlyneſs cauſe of God (for that the ſame might obtain a being-like ſhape in you,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> and ye to Lord with God and his righteouſneſs eſſentially or being-like) ye ſhall altogether forſake, hate and leave your own Lordlyneſs, or to Lord alone without God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45. Pro. 25.</note> with your ſelves, or with the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and corrupt world, and even ſo altogether give over your ſelves to Gods Lordlyneſs, and to the Elders and dayed-ones in the ſame, or to thoſe which Lord with God, for to
<pb facs="tcp:171452:113"/>
live and walk obediently only in the Lordlyneſs with God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 25.</note> according to the Ordinance of the Elders or day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-ones in the ſame, to all preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſafe-walking, and to all peace on the earth.</p>
            <p n="15">15. When ye now are well exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this ſame fourth Vertue or Godlyneſs, then ſhall ye proceed to the fifth Vertue or Godlyneſs.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Which fifth Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs is the ſtool of Gods Majeſty,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.4.</note> or the poſſeſſing of the high ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign God head.</p>
            <p n="17">17. For the Stools cauſe of Gods Majeſtie (for that ye might be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to the ſame,<note place="margin">Apo. 21. Ioh. 14. Luk. 14.</note> and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the high worthy God-head might eſſentially obtain his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing everlaſting dwelling in you) ye ſhall altogether forſake, hate and leave all your own poſſeſſing,<note place="margin">Math. 19. Heb. 2.4. Pſal. 10.3.</note> and all your own regarding of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie or high worthyneſs, and ſo alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether give over your ſelves to the Stool of Gods Majeſty, and to the
<pb facs="tcp:171452:114"/>
Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame, for to live and walk obediently and in all ſubmiſſion only in the poſſeſsing or inhabiting of the living and high worthy God-head, the Stool of Gods Majeſty, and in the Ordinance of the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> to all concord of peaceable life, of Gods peaceable Kingdom on the Earth, becauſe that the ſame peace with the peaceable Kingdom of God,<note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> and the Stool of the ſame Majeſty, might be enlarged on the Earth,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> and be obſerved to all peace and Love, and even ſo to remain everlaſtingly upon the earth, and keep the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence or over-hand,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.59.</note> under the obedience of the Love.</p>
            <p n="18">18. When ye now are well exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this fame fifth Vertue or Godlyneſs,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.7.</note> then ſhall ye proceed in the ſixth Vertue or Godlyneſs.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Which ſixth Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, is Gods Viſion of the peace of the Perfection.</p>
            <p n="20">20. For which Viſions cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:171452:114"/>
God, of the Peace, and of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection (for that ye might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the ſame cleerneſs rightly and according to truth, and become conſubſtantiated therewith,<note place="margin">Apo. 21.</note> and that the ſame Viſion of God might likewiſe obtain a being-like ſhape in you) ye ſhall altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, hate,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.</note> and leave all your own Viſion of peace, or all your Viſions wherewith ye out of the fleſh, and out of the earthly and natural,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> or bloody being, have perceived, or looked into your own peace and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection according to the fleſh, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the creaturely manner, and ſhall in the ſame Viſion become altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blind, and even ſo give over your ſelves altogether to Gods Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Peace and of the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and to the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame, for to live and walk obediently only in Gods Viſion of the Peace and Perfection, and in the Ordinance of the Elders to dreſs, maintain, and govern all things that
<pb facs="tcp:171452:115"/>
are on the Earth, in his right being eſtate or Ordinance, to an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal peace and upright Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon the earth.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note>21. When ye now are well exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this ſame ſixth Vertue or Godlyneſs, then ſhall ye proceed in the ſeventh Vertue or Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note>22. Which ſeventh Vertue or Godlyneſs is the Anointed of God, which proceedeth from the Living God, with the anointing of the joyful Oyl or comforting of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> and with all peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the heart and mind.</p>
            <p n="23">23. For which anointed ones cauſe of God (for that ye to an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right peaceableneſs of your hearts &amp; minds might become conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44. Heb. 1.</note> or of one being with the ſame, and with his anointing of the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oyl, or of the holy-Ghoſt, and that he himſelf with his holy and godly anointing might obtain a ſhape in you) ye ſhall altogether
<pb facs="tcp:171452:115"/>
forſake and leave your ſelves and all your own annointing or opinionated peaceableneſs, and your Joy or Comforting of your heart and mind, wherein ye do live to a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of your ſelves and to your own reſt according to the fleſh,<note place="margin">Iſa. 61</note> and become in all the ſame altogether dead,<note place="margin">Apo. 21.</note> and even to give over your ſelves altogether to the annointed ones of God, and to the Elders or dayed-ones in the ſame,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.</note> for to live and walk obediently, only in the annointed ones of God, and in the Ordinance of the Elders or dayed ones in the ſame,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> to all fruitfulneſs in the upright righteouſneſs and Godlyneſs upon the earth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. When ye now are well exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this ſame ſeventh Vertue or Godlyneſs then ſhall, ye proceed in the eighth Vertue or Godlyneſs, the Perfection of all Vertues or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs) and ſo go forth in the ſame.<note place="margin">Acts 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. Which eighth Vertue or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs is the new Life of the true life
<pb facs="tcp:171452:116"/>
of God the Father, of the Son, and of the holy-Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> which is full of all Vertues or Godlyneſs, full of all Love, Grace and Wiſdom, full of all power of God, all ſpiritual goods, and full of all heavenly fairneſs,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> and that ſame wherewith God keepeth his righteous Judgement over the whole world,<note place="margin">Apo. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, 22.</note> for to Judge the ſame with righteouſneſs, and wherein all mortified righteouſneſs or godly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers of Ieſus Chriſt riſe up with their bodies gloriouſly, and with everlaſting Joy and Chriſtian-like triumph live and dwell everlaſtingly in the ſame, with minds and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings of pure hearts.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.13, 15, 16.</note>26. For which lives cauſe of the true mind of the everlaſting and perfect God-head (becauſe that the ſame might obtain a being-like ſhape in you,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> and ye become of one being with the ſame, and be preſerved in the righteous Judgement of God) ye ſhall altogether forſake,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> hate, and leave all your own life, with all
<pb facs="tcp:171452:116"/>
that ſame which is engendred, or brought forth in you to a life accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> or is appeared or riſen up unto you in your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; or that which you your ſelves have procured and adopted, or taken on before the Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or before the renewing of your ſpirits and minds in the new life of the true mind of God, to a life,<note place="margin">Luk. 14. Ioh. 12.</note> until that the ſame be altogether dead; mortified and buried with you, and even ſo altogether give over your ſelves to the new life of the true mind of the everlaſting and perfect God-head and to the eldeſt or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt Elder in the ſame, for to live and walk even ſo obediently in all Love,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> only in the new life of the true minde of the everlaſting and perfect God-head, and in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Eldeſt or dayedſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones in the ſame, and even ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit in the perfection of all Vertues or Godlyneſs, with everlaſting joy, and Chriſtian-like Triumph in the
<pb facs="tcp:171452:117"/>
heavenly being, as alſo the everlaſting life. O that it might thus come to paſs even ſo.</p>
            <closer>Every one Ponder it deeply in his heart.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
